<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
]>

<section id="Document_Conventions">
		<title>Examples and Formatting</title>
		<para>
			Each of the examples used in this guide, such as file locations and commands, have certain defined conventions.
		</para>
		<section id="bracketsexamples"><title>Brackets</title>
		<para>
			Square brackets (<command>[]</command>) are used to indicate an alternative element in a name. For example, if a tool is available in <filename>/usr/lib</filename> on 32-bit systems and in <filename>/usr/lib64</filename> on 64-bit systems, then the tool location may be represented as <filename>/usr/lib[64]</filename>.
		</para>
		</section>
		<section id="tool-locations"><title>Client Tool Information</title>
			<para>
				The tools for &IPA; are located in the <filename>&BIN;</filename> and the <filename>&SBIN;</filename> directories.
			</para>
				<para>
					The LDAP tools used to edit the &IPA; directory services, such as <command>ldapmodify</command> and <command>ldapsearch</command>,
					are from OpenLDAP. OpenLDAP tools use SASL connections by default.
					To perform a simple bind using a username and password, use the <option>-x</option> argument to disable SASL.
				</para>
		</section>
		<section id="guide-formatting"><title>Text Formatting and Styles</title>
		<para>
			Certain words are represented in different fonts, styles, and weights. Different character formatting is
			used to indicate the function or purpose of the phrase being highlighted.
		</para>
		<informaltable>
			<tgroup cols="2">
				<thead>
					<row valign="top">
						<entry>
							Formatting Style
						</entry>
						<entry>
							Purpose
						</entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row valign="top">
						<entry>
<screen>Monospace with a background</screen>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							This type of formatting is used for anything entered or returned in a command prompt.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row valign="top">
						<entry>
							<emphasis>Italicized text</emphasis>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							Any text which is italicized is a variable, such as <emphasis>instance_name</emphasis>
							or <emphasis>hostname</emphasis>. Occasionally, this is also used to emphasize a new term
							or other phrase.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row valign="top">
						<entry>
							<emphasis role="bold">Bolded text</emphasis>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							Most phrases which are in bold are application names, such as <application>Cygwin</application>,
							or are fields or options in a user interface, such as a <guilabel>User Name Here:</guilabel> field
							or <guibutton>Save</guibutton> button. This can also indicate a file, package, or directory name, such as <filename>&SBIN;</filename>.
						</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</informaltable>
		<para>
			Other formatting styles draw attention to important text.
		</para>
		<note>
			<title>NOTE</title>
			<para>
				A note provides additional information that can help illustrate the behavior of the system or
				provide more detail for a specific issue.
			</para>
		</note>
		<important>
			<title>IMPORTANT</title>
			<para>
				Important information is necessary, but possibly unexpected, such as a configuration
				change that will not persist after a reboot.
			</para>
		</important>
		<warning>
			<title>WARNING</title>
			<para>
				A warning indicates potential data loss, as may happen when tuning hardware for maximum performance.
			</para>
		</warning>
	</section>
</section>

