<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
]>
<chapter id="user-pwdpolicy">
	<title>Policy: Defining Password Policies</title>
	<para>
		All users must have a password which they use to authenticate to the Kerberos domain. &PROD; defines and enforces rules about password complexity, password histories, and account lockouts
		in order to maintain security.
	</para>
		<note><title>NOTE</title>
			 <para>
				&IPA;, by default, does not expose passwords to clients, even hashed passwords, for system security.
	<!--
This policy applies even if you still rely on NIS server functionality to some degree, for example, as a result of a full or partial migration from NIS to &IPA;. &IPA; normally expects a switch to Kerberos for authentication, but this may not always be possible.
-->
			</para>
		</note>
		<section id="about-pwd-policy"><title>About Password Policies and Policy Attributes</title>
	 <para>
		A <emphasis>password policy</emphasis> sets certain standards for passwords, such as the password complexity and the rules for changing
		passwords. A password policy minimizes the inherent risk of using passwords by ensuring that they meet adequate complexity standards to thwart brute force attacks and they
		are changed frequently enough to mitigate the risk of someone revealing or discovering a password.
	</para>
	<para>
		There are three main configuration areas that are defined within the password policy:
	</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Strength or complexity requirements
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					History
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Account lockout
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
				<para>
					The &IPA; password policy is enforced jointly by the KDC and the LDAP server. While the password policy is set in the LDAP
					directory and is based on &DSF; password policy attributes, the policy is ultimately constrained by the KDC password policy
					framework. The KDC policy is less flexible than the &DSF; policy framework, so the &IPA; password policy can only implement
					password policy elements supported in the KDC. Any other policy settings made within the &DSF; are not visible or enforced in &PROD;.
				</para>
		 <para>
			Password policies are assigned either globally or to groups in &IPA;, not to individual users. The password policy is assigned a weight, so that if
			a user belongs to multiple groups with different password policies, the policy with the highest priority will take precedence.
		</para>
		<para>
			The different policy attributes that can be set are listed in <xref linkend="tab.pwpolicy-attrs" />.
		</para>
		<table id="tab.pwpolicy-attrs"><title>Password Policy Settings</title>
			<tgroup cols="3">
				<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" />
				<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" />
				<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" />
				<thead>
					<row>
						<entry>
							Configuration Property
						</entry>
						<entry>
							Command-Line Option
						</entry>
						<entry>
							Description
						</entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry namest="col1" nameend="col3">
							<emphasis role="bold">Options for both the UI and CLI</emphasis>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							Minimum Password Lifetime
						</entry>
						<entry>
							--minlife
						</entry>
						<entry>
							Sets the minimum period of time, in hours, that a user's password must be in effect before the user can change it. This can prevent a user from changing a password and then immediately changing it to the original value. The default value is one hour.
						</entry>
					</row>
			 		<row>
						<entry>
							Maximum Password Lifetime
						</entry>
						<entry>
							--maxlife
						</entry>
						<entry>
							Sets the maximum period of time, in days, that a user's password can be in effect before it must be changed. The default value is 90 days.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							Minimum Number of Character Classes
						</entry>
						<entry>
							--minclasses
						</entry>
						<entry>
							Sets the minimum number of different classes, or types, of character that must exist in a password before it is considered valid. For example, setting this value to 3 requires that any password must have characters from at least three categories in order to be approved. The default value is zero (0), meaning there are no required classes.
								<para>
					There are six character classes:
				</para>
				 <itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Upper-case characters
						</para>

					</listitem>
					 <listitem>
						<para>
							Lower-case characters
						</para>

					</listitem>
					 <listitem>
						<para>
							Digits
						</para>

					</listitem>
					 <listitem>
						<para>
							Special characters (for example, punctuation)
						</para>

					</listitem>
					 <listitem>
						<para>
							8-bit characters (characters whose decimal code starts at 128 or below)
						</para>

					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Number of repeated characters
						</para>
						 <para>
							This weights in the opposite direction, so that if you have too many repeated characters you will not meet the quorum to satisfy the "level" expressed by <property>krbPwdMinDiffChars</property>.
						</para>

					</listitem>

				</itemizedlist>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							Minimum Length of Password
						</entry>
						<entry>
							--minlength
						</entry>
						<entry>
							Sets the minimum number of characters for a password. The default value is eight characters.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							Password History
						</entry>
						<entry>
							--history
						</entry>
						<entry>
							Sets the number of previous passwords that are stored and which a user is prevented from using. For example, if this is set
							to ten, &IPA; prevents a user from reusing any of their previous ten passwords. The default value is zero (0), which disables password history.
				 <note><title>NOTE</title>
					<para>
						Even with the password history set to zero, users cannot reuse a <emphasis>current</emphasis> password.
					</para>

				</note>
						</entry>
					</row>

					<row>
						<entry namest="col1" nameend="col3">
							<emphasis role="bold">Options for the CLI only</emphasis>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							Priority
						</entry>
						<entry>
							--priority
						</entry>
						<entry>
							Sets the priority which determines which policy is in effect. The lower the number, the higher priority.
							<para>
								Although this priority is required when the policy is first created in the UI, it cannot be reset in the UI. It can only be reset using the CLI.
							</para>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							Maximum Consecutive Failures
						</entry>
						<entry>
							--maxfail
						</entry>
						<entry>
							Specifies the maximum number of consecutive failures to input the correct password before the user's account is locked.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							Fail Interval
						</entry>
						<entry>
							--failinterval
						</entry>
						<entry>
							Specifies the period (in seconds) after which the failure count will be reset.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							Lockout Time
						</entry>
						<entry>
							--lockouttime
						</entry>
						<entry>
							Specifies the period (in seconds) for which a lockout is enforced.
						</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>
	</section>

	 <section id="viewing-the_Password_Policy">
		 <title>Viewing Password Policies</title>
		 <para>
			There can be multiple password policies configured in &IPA;. There is always a global policy, which is created with the server. Additional policies can be created
			for groups in &IPA;.
		</para>
		<para>
			The UI lists all of the group password policies and the global policy on the <guilabel>Password Policies</guilabel> page.
		</para>
		 <para>
			Using the CLI, both global and group-level password policies can be viewed using the <command>pwpolicy-show</command> command. The CLI can also display the password policy in effect for a user.
		</para>
		<section id="viewing-global"><title>Viewing the Global Password Policy</title>
			<para>
				The global password policy is created with the server. This applies to every user until a group-level password policy supersedes it.
			</para>
			<para>
				The default settings for the global password policy are listed in <xref linkend="tab.default-global" />.
			</para>
			<table id="tab.default-global"><title>Default Global Password Policy</title>
				<tgroup cols="2">
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry>
								Attribute
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Value
							</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>
								Max lifetime
							</entry>
							<entry>
								90 (days)
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								Min lifetime
							</entry>
							<entry>
								1 (hour)
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								History size
							</entry>
							<entry>
								0 (unset)
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								Character classes
							</entry>
							<entry>
								0 (unset)
							</entry>
						</row>

						<row>
							<entry>
								Min length
							</entry>
							<entry>
								8
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								Max failures
							</entry>
							<entry>
								6
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								Failure reset interval
							</entry>
							<entry>
								60
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								Lockout duration
							</entry>
							<entry>
								600
							</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>
			<section id="viewing-global-pwdpolicy-u"><title>With the Web UI</title>
				<orderedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Click the <guilabel>Policy</guilabel> tab, and then click the <guilabel>Password Policies</guilabel> subtab.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							All of the policies in the UI are listed by group. The global password policy is defined by the <guilabel>global_policy</guilabel> group. Click the group link.
						</para>
						<informalfigure>
							<mediaobject>
								<imageobject>
									<imagedata fileref="images/pwd-policy-page.png" />
								</imageobject>
							</mediaobject>
						</informalfigure>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							The global policy is displayed.
						</para>
						<informalfigure>
							<mediaobject>
								<imageobject>
									<imagedata fileref="images/pwd-policy-global.png" />
								</imageobject>
							</mediaobject>
						</informalfigure>
					</listitem>
				</orderedlist>
			</section>

			<section id="viewing-global-pwdpolicy-cmd"><title>With the Command Line</title>
		<para>
			To view the global policy, simply run the <command>pwpolicy-show</command> command with no arguments:
			</para>
<screen>$ ipa pwpolicy-show

  Group: global_policy
  Max lifetime (days): 90
  Min lifetime (hours): 1
  History size: 0
  Character classes: 0
  Min length: 8
  Max failures: 6
  Failure reset interval: 60
  Lockout duration: 600</screen>
  			</section>
		</section>

		<section id="viewing-group-pwd-policies"><title>Viewing Group-Level Password Policies</title>
			<section id="viewing-group-pwdpolicy-u"><title>With the Web UI</title>
				<orderedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Click the <guilabel>Policy</guilabel> tab, and then click the <guilabel>Password Policies</guilabel> subtab.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							All of the policies in the UI are listed by group. Click the name of the group which is assigned the policy.
						</para>
						<informalfigure>
							<mediaobject>
								<imageobject>
									<imagedata fileref="images/pwd-policy-page.png" />
								</imageobject>
							</mediaobject>
						</informalfigure>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							The group policy is displayed.
						</para>
						<informalfigure>
							<mediaobject>
								<imageobject>
									<imagedata fileref="images/pwd-policy2.png" />
								</imageobject>
							</mediaobject>
						</informalfigure>
					</listitem>
				</orderedlist>
			</section>

			<section id="viewing-group-pwdpolicy-cmd"><title>With the Command Line</title>
			<para>
				For a group-level password policy, specify the group name with the command:
			</para>
<screen>$ ipa pwpolicy-show examplegroup

  Group: global_policy
  Max lifetime (days): 90
  Min lifetime (hours): 1
  History size: 3
  Character classes: 4
  Min length: 8
  Max failures: 3
  Failure reset interval: 15
  Lockout duration: 150</screen>
 		</section>
 		</section>

		<section id="viewing-pwdpolicy-user"><title>Viewing the Password Policy in Effect for a User</title>
			<para>
				A user may belong to multiple groups, each with their own separate password policies. These policies are not additive. Only one
				policy is in effect at a time and it applies to all password policy attributes. To see which policy is in effect for
				a specific user, the <command>pwpolicy-show</command> command can be run for a specific user. The results also show <emphasis>which</emphasis>
				group policy is in effect for that user.
			</para>
<screen>$ ipa pwpolicy-show --user=jsmith

  Group: admins
  Max lifetime (days): 90
  Min lifetime (hours): 1
  History size: 0
  Character classes: 0
  Min length: 8
  Max failures: 6
  Failure reset interval: 60
  Lockout duration: 600</screen>
  		</section>
	</section>


	 <section id="Setting_Different_Password_Policies_for_Different_User_Groups">
		<title>Creating and Editing Password Policies</title>
		 <para>
			A password policy can be selective; it may only define certain elements. A <emphasis>global</emphasis> password policy sets
			defaults that are used for every user entry, unless a group policy takes priority.
		</para>
		<note><title>NOTE</title>
			 <para>
				 A global policy always exists, so there is no reason to add a global password policy.
			 </para>
		 </note>
		 <para>
			Group-level policies override the global policies and offer specific policies that only apply to group members.
			Password policies are not cumulative. Either a group policy or the global policy is in effect for a user or group, but
			not both simultaneously.
		</para>
		<para>
			Group-level policies do not exist by default, so they must be created manually.
		 </para>
		 <note><title>NOTE</title>
			<para>
				It is not possible to set a password policy for a non-existent group.
			</para>

		</note>
		<section id="creating-group-policy-ui"><title>Creating Password Policies in the Web UI</title>
				<orderedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Click the <guilabel>Policy</guilabel> tab, and then click the <guilabel>Password Policies</guilabel> subtab.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							All of the policies in the UI are listed by group. The global password policy is defined by the <guilabel>global_policy</guilabel> group. Click the group link.
						</para>
						<informalfigure>
							<mediaobject>
								<imageobject>
									<imagedata fileref="images/pwd-policy-page.png" />
								</imageobject>
							</mediaobject>
						</informalfigure>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Click the <guilabel>Add</guilabel> link at the top.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							In the pop-up box, select the group for which to create the password policy.
						</para>
						<informalfigure>
							<mediaobject>
								<imageobject>
									<imagedata fileref="images/pwd-policy1a.png" />
								</imageobject>
							</mediaobject>
						</informalfigure>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Set the priority of the policy. The higher the number, the lower the priority.
						</para>
						<para>
							Only one password policy is in effect for a user, and that is the highest priority policy.
						</para>
						<informalfigure>
							<mediaobject>
								<imageobject>
									<imagedata fileref="images/pwd-policy1b.png" />
								</imageobject>
							</mediaobject>
						</informalfigure>
						<note><title>NOTE</title>
							<para>
								The priority cannot be changed in the UI once the policy is created.
							</para>
						</note>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Click the <guibutton>Add and Edit</guibutton> button so that the policy form immediately opens.
						</para>
					</listitem>

					<listitem>
						<para>
							Set the policy fields. Leaving a field blank means that attribute is not added the password policy configuration.
						</para>
						<itemizedlist>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									<emphasis>Max lifetime</emphasis> sets the maximum amount of time, in days, that a password is valid before a user must reset it.
								</para>
							</listitem>

							<listitem>
								<para>
									<emphasis>Min lifetime</emphasis> sets the minimum amount of time, in hours, that a password must remain in effect before a user is permitted to change it. This prevents a user from attempting to change a password back immediately to an older password or from cycling through the password history.
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									<emphasis>History size</emphasis> sets how many previous passwords are stored. A user cannot re-use a password that is still in the password history.
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									<emphasis>Character classes</emphasis> sets the different categories of character that must be used in the password. For example, a character class can be a number, special character, or capital; the complete list of categories is in <xref linkend="tab.pwpolicy-attrs" />. This is part of setting the complexity requirements.
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									<emphasis>Min length</emphasis> sets how many characters must be in a password. This is part of setting the complexity requirements.
								</para>
							</listitem>
						</itemizedlist>
					</listitem>
				</orderedlist>
		</section>

		<section id="creating-group-policy-cmd"><title>Creating Password Policies with the Command Line</title>
			<para>
				Password policies are added with the <command>pwpolicy-add</command> command.
			</para>
<screen>$ ipa pwpolicy-add <replaceable>groupName --attribute-value</replaceable></screen>
		 <para>
			For example:
		</para>

<screen>$ ipa pwpolicy-add exampleGroup --minlife=7 --maxlife=49 --history= --priority=1
Group: exampleGroup
Max lifetime (days): 49
Min lifetime (hours): 7
Priority: 1
</screen>
		<note><title>TIP</title>
			<para>
				Setting an attribute to a blank value effectively removes that attribute from the password policy.
			</para>
		</note>
	</section>

	<section id="edit-global-policy-cmd"><title>Editing Password Policies with the Command Line</title>
		<para>
			As with most &IPA; entries, a password policy is edited by using a <command>*-mod</command> command, <command>pwpolicy-mod</command>, and then the policy name. However, there is one difference with editing password policies: there is a global policy which always exists. Editing a group-level password policy is slightly different than editing the global password policy.
		</para>
		<para>
			Editing a group-level password policy follows the standard syntax of <command>*-mod</command> commands. It uses the <command>pwpolicy-mod</command> command, the name of the policy entry, and the attributes to change. For example:
			</para>
<screen>[jsmith@ipaserver ~]$ ipa pwpolicy-mod exampleGroup --lockouttime=300 --history=5 --minlength=8</screen>

			 <para>
				 To edit the global password policy, use the <command>pwpolicy-mod</command> command with the attributes to change, <emphasis>but without specifying a password policy name</emphasis>. For example:
			</para>
<screen>[jsmith@ipaserver ~]$ ipa pwpolicy-mod --lockouttime=300 --history=5 --minlength=8</screen>
		</section>
	</section>

	 <section id="pwd-expiration">
		 <title>Managing Password Expiration Limits</title>
		 <indexterm>
			 <primary>password expiration</primary>
		 </indexterm>
		 <indexterm>
			 <primary>password policies</primary>
			 <secondary>expiration</secondary>
		 </indexterm>
		 <indexterm>
			 <primary>users</primary>
			 <secondary>password expiration</secondary>
		 </indexterm>
			<para>
				Password policies are applied <emphasis role="bold">at the time a password is changed</emphasis>. So, when a password is set, it conforms to the password  policy in effect at that time. If the password policy is changed later, that change is not applied, retroactively, to the password.
			</para>
			<para>
				Setting password expiration periods is configured as part of the group
				password policy. Creating and editing password policies (including the expiration
				attribute in the policy) is covered in <xref linkend="Setting_Different_Password_Policies_for_Different_User_Groups" />.
			</para>
			<para>
				With password expiration periods, there are two attributes that are related:
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						The maximum lifetime setting given in the password policy (<option>--maxlife</option>)
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						The actual date that the password for a given user expires (<parameter>krbPasswordExpiration</parameter>)
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<para>
				Changing the password expiration time in the password policy does not affect the
				expiration date for a user, until the user password is changed. If the password
				expiration date needs to be changed immediately, it can be changed by editing the
				user entry.
			</para>
			<para>
				To force the expiration date to change, reset the <parameter>krbPasswordExpiration</parameter> attribute value for the user. This can be done using the &IPA; CLI with the <option>--setattr</option> option:
			</para>
<screen>[bjensen@ipaserver ~]$ kinit
[bjensen@ipaserver ~]$ ipa user-mod jsmith --setattr=krbPasswordExpiration=20121231011529Z</screen>
			<para>
				If the new expiration date should be applied to multiple entries, it may be simpler
				to use <command>ldapmodify</command> and edit multiple entries simultaneously
				through an LDIF file in the <option>-f</option> option.
				For example, editing a single entry (with a modify statement similar to the LDIF
				file in <option>-f</option>):
			</para>
<screen>[bjensen@ipaserver ~]$ ldapmodify -Y GSSAPI -h ipaserver.example.com -p 389 -vv

dn: uid=jsmith,cn=users,cn=accounts,dc=example,dc=com
changetype: modify
replace: krbpasswordexpiration
krbpasswordexpiration: 20140202203734Z
-</screen>
			<note><title>TIP</title>
				<para>
					If an administrator resets a password, it expires the previous password
					and forces the user to update the password. When the user updates the
					password, it automatically uses the new password policies, including a
					new expiration date.
				</para>
			</note>
		</section>

		 <section id="Setting_the_Priority_of_Password_Policies">
			<title>Changing the Priority of Group Password Policies</title>
				<para>
					A user may belong to multiple groups, each with different password policies. Since only one policy can be in
					effect for a user, there has to be a method to assign precedence to policies. That is done through <emphasis>priority</emphasis>.
				</para>
				<para>
					The highest priority is zero (0). The lower the number, the higher the priority.
				</para>
				<para>
					This is set initially when the password policy is created. It can be modified after the policy is created by resetting the <option>--priority</option> option.
				</para>
<screen>$ ipa pwpolicy-mod examplegroup --priority=10</screen>
				<para>
					When a user belongs to multiple groups, the group password policy with the lowest number has the priority.
				</para>
				<note><title>NOTE</title>
					<para>
						The password policy priority cannot be changed in the UI after it is created.
					</para>
				</note>
			</section>

			<section id="Setting_Account-lockout_Policies">
			<title>Setting Account Lockout Policies</title>
				<para>
					A brute force attack occurs when a malefactor attempts to guess a password by simply slamming the server with multiple login attempts. An account lockout policy prevents brute force attacks by blocking an account from logging into the system after a certain number of login failures &mdash; even if the correct password is subsequently entered.
				</para>
				<note><title>NOTE</title>
					<para>
						A user account can be manually unlocked by an administrator using the <command>ipa user-unlock</command>. Refer to <xref linkend="user-unlock" />.
					</para>
				</note>
				<section id="pwd-policy-ui"><title>In the UI</title>
				<para>
					These attributes are available in the password policy form when a group-level password policy is created or when any password policy (including the global password policy) is edited.
				</para>
				<orderedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Click the <guilabel>Policy</guilabel> tab, and then click the <guilabel>Password Policies</guilabel> subtab.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Click the name of the policy to edit.
						</para>
						<informalfigure>
							<mediaobject>
								<imageobject>
									<imagedata fileref="images/pwd-policy-page.png" />
								</imageobject>
							</mediaobject>
						</informalfigure>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Set the account lockout attribute values.
						</para>
						<informalfigure>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="images/pwd-policy-acctlockout.png" />
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</informalfigure>
				<para>
					There are three parts to the account lockout policy:
				</para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							The number of failed login attempts before the account is locked (<guilabel>Max Failures</guilabel>).
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							The time after a failed login attempt before the counter resets (<guilabel>Failure reset interval</guilabel>). Since mistakes do happen honestly, the count of failed attempts is not kept forever; it naturally lapses after a certain amount of time. This is in seconds.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							How long an account is locked after the max number of failures is reached (<guilabel>Lockout duration</guilabel>). This is in seconds.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
	</section>

	<section id="pwd-policy-cli"><title>In the CLI</title>
				<para>
					There are three parts to the account lockout policy:
				</para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							The number of failed login attempts before the account is locked (<option>--maxfail</option>).
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							How long an account is locked after the max number of failures is reached (<option>--lockouttime</option>). This is in seconds.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							The time after a failed login attempt before the counter resets (<option>--failinterval</option>). Since mistakes do happen honestly, the count of failed attempts is not kept forever; it naturally lapses after a certain amount of time. This is in seconds.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
				<para>
					These account lockout attributes can all be set when a password policy is created with <command>pwpolicy-add</command> or added later using <command>pwpolicy-mod</command>. For example:
				</para>
<screen>[jsmith@ipaserver ~]$ kinit admin
[jsmith@ipaserver ~]$ ipa pwpolicy-mod examplegroup --maxfail=4 --lockouttime=600 --failinterval=30</screen>
			</section>
		</section>

	 <section id="Using_SSH_for_Password_Authentication">
		<title>Enabling a Password Change Dialog</title>
		 <para>
			 There may be situations when a user exists in &PROD; but does not have a valid Kerberos ticket, meaning he cannot authenticate to the &IPA; domain. This is possible
			for new users or for users whose domain passwords have expired. Much like enabling password
			authentication in the web UI, it is possible to enable password-based authentication to the client. This opens up a password change dialog box to allow the user
			to reset the expired password.
		</para>
		<para>
			The password change dialog is enabled by using OpenSSH's <emphasis>challenge-response</emphasis> authentication.
		</para>
		<para>
			The challenge-response dialog is optional. In many environments, it is not necessary because SSSD can handle changing expired passwords by invoking the required PAM modules. However, using the challenge-response option in OpenSSH makes it possible to do password changes directly in PAM and to support full PAM conversations.
		</para>
		<para>
			This is not enabled by default, but it can be enabled by editing the OpenSSH configuration.
		</para>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem>
				 <para>
					Open the <filename>/etc/ssh/sshd_config</filename> file.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				 <para>
					Set <parameter>ChallengeResponseAuthentication</parameter> to <literal>yes</literal>.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>

	</section>
</chapter>

