<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
]>
<preface id="ReleaseNotes">
	<title>Release Information</title>
	<para>
		&PROD; is part of &RHEL; &RVER;, so major features, known issues, and bug fixes are covered in the &RHEL; release notes.
		This section is provided as a convenient reference for significant issues that are in &PROD; &VER;. The full list of known issues related to &PROD; is in the <ulink url="http://docs.redhat.com/docs/en-US/Red_Hat_Enterprise_Linux/6/html/6.3_Technical_Notes/authentication_issues.html">&OS; 6.3 Technical Notes</ulink>.
	</para>

	<section id="new-features"><title>New Features in 6.3</title>

		<formalpara><title>Automatic Group Membership for Users and Hosts</title>
			<para>
				Most of the policies configured in &PROD; are based on group membership, so 
				managing group membership is critical as a part of managing the policies for 
				both users and hosts. <emphasis>Automembership</emphasis> allows 
				administrators to set up filters for new users and hosts so that they are 
				assigned, automatically, to the appropriate user groups and host groups.
				Automembership, including examples, is covered in <xref linkend="automember" />.
			</para>
		</formalpara>
		<formalpara><title>Disabling User Private Groups</title>
			<para>
				On &OS; systems, every time a user is created, a corresponding, secret user group is automatically created with that new user as its only member. This is a <emphasis>user private group</emphasis>. There may be certain users or types of users which do not require a private group or the environment may already have those GIDs assigned to NIS groups or other system groups. In that case, user private group creation can be disabled. See <xref linkend="user-private-groups" />.
			</para>
		</formalpara>
		<formalpara><title>Better Web UI Performance</title>
			<para>
				A number of performance and usability changes have been made in 
				&IPA; 2.2, including improved session handling and adding support for Services4Unix Proxy. Along with overall better performance, these changes have introduced two new features for the web UI:
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Self-service management supported in Internet Explorer
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Form-based authentication for the web UI, in addition to Kerberos
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</para>
		</formalpara>
		<formalpara><title>Enhanced DNS Resource Record Support</title>
			<para>
				The way that &IPA; handles DNS resource records has been improved to make it 
				easier to create and edit records. The UI and CLI tooling have both been enhanced 
				to provide type-specific options for common resource record types. For more information, see 
				<xref linkend="managing-dnsrecord-entries" />.
			</para>
		</formalpara>
		<formalpara><title>SSH Key Management (Tech Preview)</title>
			<para>
				OpenSSH uses <emphasis>public-private key pairs</emphasis> to authenticate hosts. 
				The machine then stores user and host public keys in a central file, such as the
			<filename>known_hosts</filename> file.
			Clients can simple check that central key file and then grant access automatically 
			to approved users and hosts. However, since all of those files are created locally, 
			it can be difficult to maintain host and user key files across an entire enterprise. 
			The System Security Services Daemon (SSSD) can be configured to cache and retrieve 
			SSH keys so that applications and services only have to look in one location for keys. 
			Because SSSD can use &PROD; as one of its identity information providers, &PROD; 
			provides a universal and centralized repository of keys. For more information, see 
			<xref linkend="user-keys" />.
			</para>
		</formalpara>
	</section>    

	
	<section id="upgrade-notes"><title>Upgrade Notes for &IPA; 2.2</title>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Upgrade procedures are covered in <xref linkend="upgrading" />.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Existing replicas and servers in a domain can use different versions of &IPA;. However, when creating a new replica, the new replica must be the same version as the master server which it is being created from.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Because of UI session enhancements in &IPA; 2.2, it is no longer necessary to enable ticket-granting ticket (TGT) creation for browser sessions. For existing &IPA; servers, a new <filename>configure.jar</filename> file can be created that no longer enables TGT delegation as part of client browser configuration. For existing &IPA; clients, TGT delegation can be disabled again in the browser. This is covered in <xref linkend="ticket-delegation" />.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					In &IPA; 2.1, it was possible to enable password-based authentication by editing the <filename>ipa.conf</filename> file:
				</para>
<screen>vim /etc/httpd/conf.d/ipa.conf

KrbMethodNegotiate off
KrbMethodK5Passwd on</screen>
				<para>
					Because of the changes and enhancements to browser authentication mechanisms, this  <filename>ipa.conf</filename> file is updated as part of the upgrade process, and any changes are overwritten.
				</para>
				<para>
					Since &IPA; 2.2. supports form-based authentication automatically, it is now possible to log in using a username and password without having to modify the  <filename>ipa.conf</filename> file. See <xref linkend="form-based-auth" />.
				</para>
				<note><title>NOTE</title>
					<para>
						Any time a file is replaced during upgrade, a backup is made.
						If other edits were made to the <filename>ipa.conf</filename> file, the backup can be used to restore them.
					</para>
				</note>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</section>

	<section id="fixed-three"><title>Fixed in 6.3</title>
		<para>
			These issues have been resolved in &IPA; 2.2.
		</para>
		<table id="tab.fixed-issues"><title>Fixed Bugs in 6.3</title>
			<tgroup cols="2">
				<thead>
					<row>
						<entry>
							Bugzilla
						</entry>
						<entry>
							Description
						</entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>
					<ulink url="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=736074">Bugzilla 736074</ulink>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							In the directory, calling <function>hash_create()</function> with an initial table size of 65536 corrupted memory. With the default parameters, the corruption could occur if the initial table size was larger than 1024.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<ulink url="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=743680">Bugzilla 743680</ulink>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							
				<para>
	    When &IPAA; server was installed with a custom hostname that was not resolvable, the
	    <command>ipa-server-install</command> command failed to add a record to the static hostname lookup table in
	    <filename>/etc/hosts</filename>, which prevented further configuration of Identity Management integrated
	    services. 
    </para>
    <para>
	    The record is now properly added to <filename>/etc/hosts</filename> when an IP address is passed as
	    an CLI option and not interactively. 
	    			</para>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<ulink url="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=751776">Bugzilla 751776</ulink>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							
				<para>
					If a zone entry contained an invalid record, the entire zone failed to load. None of the records in the DNS zone, including root records, were serviced.
				</para>
				<para>
					Now, the DNS zone loads and skips the invalid resource record. All of the other DNS resource entries are served, can be resolved, and respond to requests.
				</para>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<ulink url="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=754539">Bugzilla 754539</ulink>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							Once a connection between a replica and server was deleted using <command>ipa-replica-manage del</command>, a new connection could not be created. It failed with this error:
<screen>unexpected error: list index out of range</screen>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<ulink url="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=759100">Bugzilla 759100</ulink>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							The &IPA; server could not be installed on a machine with a dual NIC. When two DNS A records existed for the same hostname, the installer failed with this error:
<screen>Server host name [server1.example.com]: 

Warning: skipping DNS resolution of host server1.example.com
The domain name has been calculated based on the host name.

Please confirm the domain name [example]: 

Unable to resolve IP address for host name
Please provide the IP address to be used for this host name:</screen>
					</entry>
				</row>
			</tbody>
		</tgroup>
		</table>
	</section>

	<section id="knownissues"><title>Known Issues in 6.3</title>

		<section><title>A Note on Internet Explorer Support on Windows</title>
			<para>
				The enhancements for Services4Unix Proxy support have made steps in adding support to use the &IPA; web UI on Internet Explorer on Windows. However, this is still 
				a nascent feature. <emphasis role="bold">In &IPA; 2.2, Internet Explorer can be used for self-service management, such as resetting account details and changing 
				passwords.</emphasis>
			</para>
			<para>
				When using Internet Explorer to perform other tasks in the &IPA; web UI, there can be issues with UI performance and layout or some operations
				may not be possible. 
			</para>
			<para>
				These are some of the known issues specifically for Internet Explorer and the web UI:
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
While the browser window is not maximized or many users are logged into the WebUI, scrolling down a page to select a user may not work properly. As soon as the user's checkbox is selected, the scroll bar jumps back up without selecting the user. This error also occurs when a permission is added to a privilege. (<ulink url="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=831299">Bugzilla 831299</ulink>) 
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
When attempting to edit a service, the edit page for that service may occasionally be blank, or show only labels for Principal or Service without showing their values. When adding a service, under certain conditions, the drop-down menu lists the available services and hosts but users are unable to select any of the entries. (<ulink url="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=831227">Bugzilla 831227</ulink>) 
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
When adding a permission of type subtree, the text area to specify the subtree is too small and non-resizable making it difficult to enter long subtree entries. (<ulink url="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=830817">Bugzilla 830817</ulink>) 
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
When adding a delegation, its attributes are separated by disproportionately large vertical spaces. (<ulink url="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=829899">Bugzilla 829899</ulink>) 
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
When adding a member, the edge of the displayed window suggests it can be resized. However, resizing of the window does not work. When adding a sudo command to a sudo command group, the first group overlays with the column title. (<ulink url="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=829746">Bugzilla 829746</ulink>) 
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
Adding a new DNS zone causes the window to be incorrectly rendered as text on the existing page. (<ulink url="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=827583">Bugzilla 827583</ulink>) 
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</section>

		<section><title>List of Issues</title>
		<table id="tab.known-issues"><title>Known Issues in 6.3</title>
			<tgroup cols="3">
				<thead>
					<row>
						<entry>
							Bugzilla
						</entry>
						<entry>
							Description
						</entry>
						<entry>
							Workaround
						</entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<emphasis role="bold">SELinux mapping is not working.</emphasis>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							The SELinux mapping feature was intended to be a tech preview feature in &RHEL; 6.3. This feature is disabled, pending further development. The SELinux mapping area in the web UI and the SELinux mapping-related tools are non-functional.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<ulink url="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=724911">Bugzilla 724911</ulink>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							It is not possible to change the <parameter>uidNumber</parameter> or <parameter>gidNumber</parameter> of a user when using SSSD. SSSD caches the authentication information; when the user is deleted and re-added with a new <parameter>uidNumber</parameter> number, then SSSD attempts to reuse the cached object for the new user, which fails wit this error:
<screen>Cache file [/tmp/krb5cc_1866400007_wPJrHJ] exists, but is owned by [1866400007] instead of [1866400008].</screen>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							If the UID or GID number is ever changed for an account, then go to each local SSSD client and purge the cache. The SSSD cache purge tool is described in the <citetitle>&OS; &OVER; &DPG;</citetitle>.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<ulink url="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=726456">Bugzilla 726456</ulink>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							SSSD does not support the LDAP password expiration controls, so it does not support password expiration notifications or warnings. The &DSF; instance used by &PROD; does support these controls.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<ulink url="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=741264">Bugzilla 741264</ulink>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							The way that &AD; performs referrals is different than the way that the OpenLDAP libraries (used by the &DSF; instance in &PROD;) perform referrals. Intermittently, &AD; may return a referral during an LDAP bind attempt that is denied by the OpenLDAP libraries. This can cause performance problems, information loss, or for SSSD to go offline.
						</entry>
						<entry>
							Set this parameter in <filename>sssd.conf</filename>:
<screen>ldap_referrals = False</screen>
					This disables referral chasing in SSSD.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<ulink url="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=741957">Bugzilla 741957</ulink>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							When updating the list of object classes for a user or group entry, it is possible to delete object classes which are required by &IPA;. The UI and CLI do not prevent the required object classes from being deleted, but adding a user or group after the change will fail with object class violations.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<ulink url="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=742263">Bugzilla 742263</ulink>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							The previous and next buttons were not displayed in the UI if the number of entries returned is 
					larger than the configured size limit.
						</entry>
						<entry>
							Increase the number of entries displayed in a search to a reasonable level.
					This is described in <xref linkend="search-limits" />.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<ulink url="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=743680">Bugzilla 743680</ulink>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							When &IPAA; server is installed with a custom hostname that is not resolvable, the
	    <command>ipa-server-install</command> command should add a record to the static hostname lookup table in
	    <filename>/etc/hosts</filename> and enable further configuration of Identity Management integrated
	    services. However, a record is not added to <filename>/etc/hosts</filename> when an IP address is passed as
	    an CLI option and not interactively. Consequently, &IPA; server installation fails because integrated
	    services that are being configured expect the &IPA; server hostname to be resolvable. 
						</entry>
						<entry>
							There are two ways to work around this issue:
				<itemizedlist>
	      <listitem>
		<para>Run the <command>ipa-server-install</command> without the <option>--ip-address</option> option and pass the IP address interactively.</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  Add a record to <filename>/etc/hosts</filename> before the installation is started. The record should
		  contain the Identity Management server IP address and its full hostname (the
		  <command>hosts(5)</command> man page specifies the record format).
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<ulink url="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=743945">Bugzilla 743945</ulink>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							Searches can be performed on attributes that are not displayed in the UI. This means that 
					entries can be returned in a search that do not appear to match the given filter. This is especially 
					common if the search information is very short, which increases the likelihood of a match.
						</entry>
						<entry>
							For more information on setting and changing attributes which are searched, see <xref linkend="search-fields" />
					and <xref linkend="search-fields-groups" />.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<ulink url="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=745575">Bugzilla 745575</ulink>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							On the configuration page of the Identity Management web UI, if the <guilabel>User</guilabel> search field is left blank, and the <guibutton>search</guibutton> button is clicked, an internal error is returned.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<ulink url="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=749357">Bugzilla 749357</ulink> and <ulink url="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=750596">Bugzilla 750596</ulink>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							<para>
								The &IPA; information is stored in a separate LDAP directory than the certificate information, and these two LDAP databases are replicated separately. It is possible for a replication agreement to be broken for one directory and working for another, which can cause problems with managing clients.
				</para>
				<para>
					For example, &IPAA; server and replica have a function replication agreement between their &IPA; databases, but the replication agreement between their CA databases is broken. If a host is created on the server, the host entry is replicated over to the replica &mdash; but the certificate for that host is not replicated. The replica is aware of the client, but any management operations for that client will fail because the replica doesn't have a copy of its certificate.
				</para>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							The CA replication agreement can be recreated using the <command>ipa-csreplica-manage</command> utility.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<ulink url="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=751694">Bugzilla 751694</ulink>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							Installing the &IPA; client fails if the 32-bit packages are installed on a 64-bit system because required NSS dependencies are not installed.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<ulink url="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=752181">Bugzilla 752181</ulink>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							If any previous version of Red Hat Enterprise IPA or the &PROD; tech preview are installed, they must be uninstalled before the latest version of &PROD; can be installed and configured. Otherwise, there are problems connecting to the &PROD; LDAP server.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<ulink url="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=754739">Bugzilla 754739</ulink>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							When a replica is uninstalled, the <command>ipa-replica-manage list</command> command still lists the replica as being in the server topology.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<ulink url="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=754973">Bugzilla 754973</ulink>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							<para>
								The <command>ipa-replica-manage</command> script manages both replication agreements between &IPA; servers and synchronization agreements between &IPAA; server and an &AD; server. 
				</para>
				<para>
					The <option>force-sync</option>, <option>del</option>, and <option>re-initialize</option> subcommands with <command>ipa-replica-manage</command> do not work when managing sync agreements, so these operations fail when run against an &AD; server.
				</para>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<ulink url="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=755436">Bugzilla 755436</ulink>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							The <parameter>uidNumber</parameter> and <parameter>gidNumber</parameter> attributes on &AD; user entries are not synced over to &IPA;.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<ulink url="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=783502">Bugzilla 783502</ulink>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							The Identity Management permission plug-in does not verify that the set of attributes specified for a new permission is relevant to the target object type that the permission allows access to. This means a user is able to create a permission which allows access to attributes that will never be present in the target object type because such attributes are not allowed in its object classes. You must ensure that the chosen set of attributes for which a new permission grants access to is relevant to the chosen target object type. 
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<ulink url="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=785201">Bugzilla 785201</ulink>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							&AD; users synced to the &IPA; server are not added to the global <command>ipausers</command> group.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<ulink url="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=786629">Bugzilla 786629</ulink>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							Because a permission does not provide write access to an entry, delegation does not work as expected. 
							<para>
								The &DSF; distinguishes between access to entries and access to attributes. For example, an entry can be granted add or delete access, whereas an attribute can be granted read, search, and write access. 
							</para>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							<para>
								To grant write access to an entry, the list of writable attributes needs to be provided. The filter, subtree, and other options are used to target those entries which are writable. Attributes define which parts of those entries are writable. As a result, the list of attributes will be writable to members of the permission. 
							</para>
							
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<ulink url="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=790513">Bugzilla 790513</ulink>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							The <package>ipa-client</package> package does not install the <package>policycoreutils</package> package as its dependency, which may cause install or uninstall issues when using the <command>ipa-client-install</command> setup script.
						</entry>
						<entry>
							Install the <package>policycoreutils</package> package manually: 
<screen>~]# yum install policycoreutils</screen>
							
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<ulink url="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=794882">Bugzilla 794882</ulink>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							When adding members to netgroups, if a host that is not configured in &IPA; already, that host is considered to be an external host. This host can be controlled with netgroups, but the &IPA; domain has no knowledge of it. Currently, there is no way to use the <command>netgroup-find</command> command to search for external hosts. 
							<para>
								When an external host is added to the netgroup coniguration, it is not automatically converted in the netgroup rule. <!-- ?? -->
							</para>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<ulink url="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=804605">Bugzilla 804605</ulink>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							&PROD; and the <command>mod_ssl</command> module should not be installed on the same system. <command>mod_ssl</command> holds the <command>mod_proxy</command> hooks, which prevents &PROD; from issuing certificates.
						</entry>
						<entry>
							Uninstall <command>mod_ssl</command>.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<ulink url="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=813376">Bugzilla 813376</ulink>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							Updating the LDAP configuration when the system upgrades, which is done with the <command>ipa-ldap-updater</command> utility, fails with a traceback error when executed by a non-root user. The SASL EXTERNAL bind attempt requires root privileges. To workaround this, update the LDAP configuration as root.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<ulink url="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=812127">Bugzilla 812127</ulink>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							&IPA; relies on the LDAP schema to know what type of data to expect in a given attribute. If, in certain situations (such as replication), attribute values that do not meet those expectations are inserted for an attribute, IPA will not be able to handle the entry, and LDAP tools must be used to manually clean up that entry. 
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<ulink url="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=812122">Bugzilla 812122</ulink>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							In &IPA;, <command>sudo</command> commands are not case sensitive, but on the operating system, commands are treated as different if they are different cases. This can lead to conflicts in &IPA; <command>sudo</command> policy. For example, when executing these two commands, the second command fails because &IPA; treats both commands the same.
<screen>~]$ ipa sudocmd-add /usr/bin/X
?
~]$ ipa sudocmd-add /usr/bin/x
ipa: ERROR: sudo command with name "/usr/bin/x" already exists</screen>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<ulink url="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=817121">Bugzilla 817121</ulink>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							In some circumstances, deleting a DNS record entry in the web UI can leave the DNS zone entry visible in the UI. This is strictly a display issue; the underlying DNS data are correctly updated and the zone is deleted.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<ulink url="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=817878">Bugzilla 817878</ulink>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							If an invalid value is given for the <emphasis>Seconds Latitude</emphasis>
					field in the configuration for a DNS location (LOC) record, the 
					server throws this error:
<screen>[Tue May 01 09:44:59 2012] [error] ipa: ERROR: non-public: InvalidOperation: quantize result has too many digits for current context</screen>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<ulink url="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=822350">Bugzilla 822350</ulink>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							When a user is migrated from an LDAP directory, the user's entry in the LDAP directory does not contain Kerberos credentials needed for a Kerberos login. When the user visits the password migration page, Kerberos credentials are generated for the user and logging in with Kerberos authentication works as expected. 
							<para>
								However, Identity Management does not generate the credentials correctly if the migrated password does not follow the password policy set on the Identity Management server. Consequently, when the password migration is done and a user tries to log in with Kerberos authentication, the user is prompted to change the password. However, the password change itself is unsuccessful, so the user is unable to log into Kerberos.
							</para>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							An administrator can reset the password of a migrated user with the <command>ipa passwd</command> command. When reset, the user's Kerberos credentials are properly generated. 
							
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<ulink url="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=826731">Bugzilla 826731</ulink>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							If configuring the CA fails, the entire server installation fails, but the 
command output is unclear where or why the installation attempt failed. To troubleshoot installation failures, check the server installation log, <filename>/var/log/ipaserver-install.log</filename>, and the CA installation log, <filename>/var/log/pki-ca-install.log</filename>.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<ulink url="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=826790">Bugzilla 826790</ulink>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							Disabling password expiration (--maxlife=0 and --minlife=0) in the default <command>global_policy</command> sets users' password expiration to 90 days.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>
							<ulink url="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=826973">Bugzilla 826973</ulink>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							When Identity Management is installed using an external CA to sign its CA certificate, the installation is processed in two steps. In the first step, a certificate request is generated to be signed by an external CA. The second step submits a file with the new signed certificate for the Identity Management CA and the certificate of the external CA.
							<para>
								During the second step of the installation, a signed Identity Management CA certificate subject is validated. However, the certificate subject validation procedure does not pull the subject of the certificate. This means that the validation step fails, unless the subject name is manually supplied.
							</para>
						</entry>
						<entry>
							When running the second step of the installation, use
							the <option>--subject</option> option to give the subject 
							nname of the certificate; by default, this is <command>O=</command><emphasis>REALM</emphasis>, and <emphasis>REALM</emphasis> is the name of the new &IPA; Kerberos realm. If a custom subject was used for the first stage of the installation, use its value instead. 
						</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>
	</section>
	</section>
</preface>

