<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE appendix PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
]>
<appendix id="tools-reference">
	<title>&IPA; Tools Reference</title>
	<para>
		&PROD; provides a variety of command-line tools that can be used to manage &IPA; servers and clients, 
		allowing an extensive range of functionality that can be managed remotely, scheduled, or scripted.
	</para>

	<section id="special-chars"><title>Using Special Characters with &IPA; Tools</title>
		<para>
			The &IPA; command-line tools are run as any other utilities in a shell. If there are special characters
			in the command &mdash; such as angle brackets (> and &lt;), ampersands (&amp;), asterisks (*), and pipes (|)
			&mdash; the characters must be escaped. Otherwise, the command fails because the shell cannot properly parse the 
			unescaped characters.
		</para>
	</section>


	<section id="ipa"><title>ipa</title>
		<para>
			The primary &PROD; command-line tool is the <command>ipa</command> command. This command has several 
			dozen subcommands, grouped by configuration areas, to give specific control over different areas of the 
			&IPA; domain configuration. These subcommands are really plug-ins, that are implemented and called through 
			the <command>ipa</command> command.
		</para>
		<para>
			One crucial feature of the <command>ipa</command> command is that it is <emphasis>pluggable</emphasis>. 
			Custom behavior can be defined for the &IPA; domain through custom <command>ipa</command> subcommands.
		</para>
			<section id="ipa-location"><title>Location</title>
				<informaltable>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Description
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Location
								</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Tool directory
								</entry>
								<entry>
									&BIN;
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Package
								</entry>
								<entry>
									ipa-admintools
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</informaltable>
			</section>

			<section id="ipa-syntax"><title>Syntax</title>
				<cmdsynopsis>
					<command>ipa</command>
					<arg choice="opt">
						<replaceable>global_options</replaceable>
					</arg>
					<arg choice="plain">
						<replaceable>commands</replaceable>
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						<replaceable>command_options</replaceable>
					</arg>
				</cmdsynopsis>

				
					<para>
						The <command>ipa</command> command is essentially 
						a big plug-in container. It supports dozens of subcommands; these subcommands are actually plug-ins which manage specific types of objects in &PROD;.
					</para>
					<para>
						The first type of a subcommand identifies the object type (such as user, sudo, group, host, or dns), and the second part identifies the operation being performed on that object.
					</para>
<screen>ipa <replaceable>objectType-operation objectName --option=value</replaceable></screen>
					<para>

					For example, adding a user is done using the 
					<command>user-add</command> subcommand:
				</para>
<screen>ipa user-add <replaceable>entryName options</replaceable></screen>

			<para>
				All topic or command areas follow a consistent pattern for how entries are managed.
			</para>
			
			<section id="tools-command-adding"><title>Adding, Editing, and Deleting Entries with ipa</title>
				<para>
					New entries are added using an <emphasis>*-add</emphasis> command. For example:
				</para>
<screen>$ ipa user-add jsmith</screen>
				<para>
					For <command>add</command> operations, commands usually prompt for any required configuration attributes, which can be passed as command-line options or using <option>--set/addattr</option> options (<xref linkend="tools-using-setattr-addattr" />).
				</para>
<screen>$ ipa user-add
First name: John
Last name: Smith
User login [jsmith]: jsmith
--------------------
Added user "jsmith"
--------------------
...</screen>
				<para>
					Likewise, entries are usually edited through a <command>*-mod</command> commands, and then any new or edited attributes are listed as options after it.
				</para>
<screen>$ ipa user-mod jsmith --title="Editor III"</screen>
				<para>
					Last, entries can be deleted using the <command>*-del</command> command and the entry's name.
				</para>
<screen>$ ipa user-del jsmith</screen>
			</section>

			<section id="tools-command-displaying"><title>Finding and Displaying Entries with ipa</title>
				<para>
					Entries for an entire type are searched for using the <command>*-find</command> command and an optional search criterion. The criterion is a string which can either be an exact match or use an asterisk (*) as a wildcard.
				</para>
<screen>ipa user-find *smith</screen>
				<para>
					With no search criterion, every entry of that type is displayed.
				</para>
				<para>
					Searches (any <command>*-find</command> command) have certain limits imposed as part of the server configuration, specifically how many entries are returned (size limits) and how long a search will run (time limits). This is covered in <xref linkend="search-limits" />. 
				Part of the server configuration is setting global defaults for size and time limits on searches. While these limits are always enforced in the web UI, they can be overridden with any <command>*-find</command> command with the <option>--sizelimit</option> and <option>--timelimit</option> options.
				For example, if the default time limit is 60 seconds and a search is going to take longer, the time limit can be increased to 120 seconds:
			</para>
<screen>[jsmith@ipaserver ~]$ ipa user-find *sen --timelimit=120</screen>
				<para>
					Not every possible attribute in an entry type can be searched for. A certain subset of attributes are predefined and indexed for searches. (This list is configurable for users and groups, but not for other types of entries.)
				</para>
				<para>
					When entries are returned, only certain default attributes are displayed with the entry; to return all attributes currently set for entries, use the <option>--all</option> option.
				</para>
				<para>
					To display a specific entry, use the <command>*-show</command> command and the entry name. As with searches, only a subset of attributes are displayed with the entry unless the <option>--all</option> option is used.
				</para>
			</section>

			<section id="tools-command-members"><title>Adding Members to Groups and Containers with ipa</title>
				<para>
					Group members are added and removed with separate commands, apart from simply modifying an entry. Member commands essentially create a relationship between different &IPA; entries. While this is obvious in traditional group-member roles, it is also true for some policy entries (like SELinux and sudo policies) where entries are associated with another entry.
				</para>
				<para>
					Most commonly, the command format for adding a member entry is <command>*-add-member</command>, although the command may specify an entry type, such as <command>*-add-user</command>.
				</para>
				<para>
					Likewise, entries are removed as members (not deleted) using a <command>*-remove-member</command> or <command>*-remove-</command><emphasis>type</emphasis> command.
					</para>
			</section>

			<section id="tools-positional-arguments"><title>Positional Elements in ipa Commands</title>
				<para>
					Usually, <command>ipa</command> subcommands have only two elements: the name of the entry being modified (the <emphasis>object</emphasis>) and then any options available for the subcommand:
				</para>
				<screen>ipa <replaceable>command entryName --options=values</replaceable></screen>
				<para>
					With a few types of entries, however, not only the entry name itself needs to be specified; the entry's <emphasis>parent</emphasis> must also be specified. This is the case with <command>automount</command> commands, for example. With automount, the location must be included whenever a new key or map is created. 
				</para>
				<para>
					The parent entry name is given first, and then the child entry name. For example, for automount, the location is given first, and then the map or key entry name.
				</para>
<screen>ipa <replaceable>command parentEntryName childEntryName --childOptions=childValues</replaceable></screen>
				</section>
			</section>
					
			<section id="ipa-topics"><title>Help Topics</title>
				
		<para>
			All of the <command>ipa</command> plug-ins (subcommands) are loosely organized in groups, based on the configuration area that they relate to. 
			These groups are called <emphasis>topics</emphasis>, and the <command>ipa</command> help information can be called 
			for each topic group.
		</para>
<screen>$ ipa help <replaceable>topicName</replaceable></screen>
		<para>
			For example, to view the description of how &IPA; handles automount and a list of all 
			commands for managing automount configuration, view the help topic for <emphasis>automount</emphasis>:
		</para>
<screen>$ ipa help automount</screen>

				<informaltable>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Topic
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Description
								</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>
  automount
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Adding and managing automount and NFS configuration.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
  cert
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Managing certificate operations.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
  config
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Managing the &IPA; server configuration.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
  delegation
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Setting and controlling authorization delegated between groups.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
  dns
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Creating and managing the DNS entries within the &IPA; DNS domain.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
  group
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Creating groups of users.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
  hbac
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Setting and testing host-based access controls.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
  host
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Creating and managing client (host) entries within the &IPA; domain.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
  hostgroup
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Creating and managing groups of hosts.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
  krbtpolicy
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Managing the Kerberos ticket policy.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
  migration
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Managing migration to &IPA;.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
  misc
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Viewing current environment variables and plug-ins.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
  netgroup
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Managing netgroups within the &IPA; domain.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
  passwd
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Managing user passwords.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
  permission
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Setting access control rules for users, groups, and roles within &IPA; to &IPA; resources.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
  privilege
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Managing a group of permissions.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
  pwpolicy
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Managing the &IPA; domain password policy.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
  role
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Creating and managing user roles, as part of access control.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
  selfservice
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Managing rights that users have to their own personal &IPA; entries.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
  service
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Creating and managing system services that are managed as an &IPA; resource.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
  sudo
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Creating and managing sudo rules and policies.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
  user
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Creating and managing &IPA; user accounts.
  								</entry>
  							</row>
  						</tbody>
  					</tgroup>
				</informaltable>	
			</section>

		
				
			<section id="ipa-global-options"><title>Global Options</title>
				<para>
					Global options are available to every subcommand.
				</para>
				<informaltable>
					<tgroup cols="3">
						
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Short Option
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Long Option
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Description
								</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>
									-h 
								</entry>
								<entry>
									--help
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Prints the help for the command and exits.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									-e <emphasis>key=value</emphasis>
								</entry>
								<entry>
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Sets a given environment variable (<emphasis>key</emphasis>) to the specified value before running the command.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									-c <emphasis>file</emphasis>
								</entry>
								<entry>
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Loads the server configuration from a different file instead of <filename>default.conf</filename>.
								</entry>
							</row>
							
							<row>
								<entry>
									-d
								</entry>
								<entry>
									--debug
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Uses debug logging when running the command.
								</entry>
							</row>
							
							<row>
								<entry>
									-v 
								</entry>
								<entry>
									--verbose
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Prints verbose messages to stdout when running the command. If two <option>-v</option> options are used, then the command returns the full XML-RPC request.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									-a
								</entry>
								<entry>
									--prompt-all
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Prompts for every argument for the command, even optional ones.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									-n
								</entry>
								<entry>
									--no-prompt
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Does not prompt for any argument, even required ones.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									-f 
								</entry>
								<entry>
									--no-fallback
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Uses only the server specified in the local <filename>default.conf</filename> and does not fallback to another server if that one is unavailable.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
								</entry>
								<entry>
									--all
								</entry>
								<entry>
									<emphasis>For find and show commands.</emphasis> Returns all of the attributes for the entry, not just the ones related to the command or configuration area.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
								</entry>
								<entry>
									--raw
								</entry>
								<entry>
									<emphasis>For find and show commands.</emphasis> Returns the raw, LDIF-formatted LDAP entry instead of the friendly-formatted versions.
								</entry>
							</row>
							
							<row>
								<entry>
								</entry>
								<entry>
									--addattr=<emphasis>attribute=value</emphasis>
								</entry>
								<entry>
									<emphasis>For add and mod commands.</emphasis> Adds a new attribute with the given value.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
								</entry>
								<entry>
									--setattr=<emphasis>attribute=value</emphasis>
								</entry>
								<entry>
									<emphasis>For add and mod commands.</emphasis> Replaces the value of a given attribute with the new value.
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</informaltable>
			</section>

			


			<section id="tools-using-setattr-addattr"><title>Managing Attributes with --setattr, --addattr, and --delattr</title>

				<para>
					All identities and configuration in &PROD; are stored as LDAP entries, with standard attribute-value assertions (AVAs). Whether an entry is created through the UI or the CLI, there are certain attributes which are required and others which are available, depending on the default and custom object classes for that entry type. 
				</para>
				<para>
					For the most common attributes, the <command>ipa</command> use specified command-line arguments to set values. For example, adding a mail attribute to a user can be done with the <option>--mail</option> argument; enabling dynamic updates for a DNS zone can be done with the <option>--allow-dynupdate</option> option with zone commands; and a map key for an automount map is given in the <option>--key</option> option. 
				</para>
				<para>
					However, entries can also allow attributes that may not have command-line (or UI) options for setting them. Partially, this is because the underlying LDAP schema is very rich, particularly for user entries, with many possible allowed attributes. Additionally, &PROD; allows schema extensions for users and groups, and those custom schema elements are not necessarily reflected in the UI or command-line tools.
				</para>
				<para>
					Any supported attribute can be added or edited to an entry using the <option>--setattr</option> and <option>--addattr</option> options.
				</para>
				<para>
					Both options have this format:
				</para>
<screen>--setattr=<replaceable>attribute=value</replaceable></screen>
				<para>
					The <option>--setattr</option> option sets one value for the given attribute; any existing values are overwritten, even for multi-valued attributes. 
				</para>
				<para>
					The <option>--addattr</option> option adds a new value for an attribute; for a multi-valued attribute, it adds the new value while preserving any existing values. 
				</para>
				<para>
					Both <option>--setattr</option> option and <option>--addattr</option> can be used multiple times in the same command invocation. For example:
				</para>
<screen>$ ipa user-mod jsmith --addattr=mail=johnnys@me.com --addattr=mail=jsmith@example.com --setattr=description="backup IT manager for the east coast branch"</screen>
				<para>
					Likewise, an attribute or specific attribute value can be removed from an entry using the <option>--delattr</option> option. For a single-valued attribute, this removes the attribute; for a multi-valued attribute, it removes only the specified value. For example:
				</para>
<screen>$ ipa user-mod jsmith --delattr=mail=johnnys@me.com</screen>
				<note><title>NOTE</title>
					<para>
						Deleting attributes is evaluated last, after adding or editing attributes. If the same attribute is added and deleted in the same modify operation, it is a no-op.
					</para>
<screen>$ ipa user-mod jsmith --addattr=mail=johnnys@me.com --delattr=mail=johnnys@me.com</screen>
				</note>
			</section>


			<section id="ipa-return-codes"><title>Return Codes</title>
				<informaltable>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Return Code
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Description
								</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>
									0 
								</entry>
								<entry>
									An error occurred.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									1
								</entry>
								<entry>
									The operation was successful.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									2
								</entry>
								<entry>
									A resource or object was not found.
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</informaltable>
			</section>

				

			<section id="ipa-commands"><title>Commands</title>

				
						<table><title>dnsrecord* Commands</title>
							<tgroup cols="2">
								<thead>
									<row>
										<entry>
											Command
										</entry>
										<entry>
											Description
										</entry>
									</row>
								</thead>
								<tbody>
									<row>
										<entry>

dnsrecord-add
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Creates a new DNS zone in the &IPA; server.
									</entry>
								</row>
									<row>
										<entry>
dnsrecord-del
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Deletes a DNS zone from the DNS domain maintained by the &IPA; server.
									</entry>
								</row>
									<row>
										<entry>
dnsrecord-find        
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Searches for a DNS zone which matches the filter.
									</entry>
								</row>
									<row>
										<entry>
dnsrecord-mod          
									
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Edits the configuration of an existing DNS domain. 
									</entry>
								</row>
									<row>
										<entry>

dnsrecord-show      
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Lists the details for any or all DNS zones, depending on the filter
									</entry>
								</row>
							</tbody>
						</tgroup>
					</table>
			
						<table><title>dnszone-* Commands</title>
							<tgroup cols="2">
								<thead>
									<row>
										<entry>
											Command
										</entry>
										<entry>
											Description
										</entry>
									</row>
								</thead>
								<tbody>
									<row>
										<entry>

dnszone-add
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Creates a new DNS zone in the &IPA; server.
									</entry>
								</row>
									<row>
										<entry>
dnszone-del
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Deletes a DNS zone from the DNS domain maintained by the &IPA; server.
									</entry>
								</row>
									<row>
										<entry>
dnszone-find        
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Searches for a DNS zone which matches the filter.
									</entry>
								</row>
									<row>
										<entry>
dnszone-mod          
									
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Edits the configuration of an existing DNS domain. 
									</entry>
								</row>
									<row>
										<entry>

dnszone-show      
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Lists the details for any or all DNS zones, depending on the filter
									</entry>
								</row>
									<row>
										<entry>
dnszone-disable             
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Disables a DNS zone, which removes it from being used but does not delete the zone or its configuration.
									</entry>
								</row>
									<row>
										<entry>
dnszone-enable          
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Enables an existing DNS zone, which restores it to the &IPA; domain with its previous configuration intact.
									</entry>
								</row>
							</tbody>
						</tgroup>
					</table>
				</section>


			<section id="ipa-commands" condition="reviewing"><title>Commands</title>
				<informaltable>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Command
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Description
								</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>

automountkey-add               Create a new automount key.
automountkey-del               Delete an automount key.
automountkey-find              Search for an automount key.
automountkey-mod               Modify an automount key.
automountkey-show              Display an automount key.
automountlocation-add          Create a new automount location.
automountlocation-del          Delete an automount location.
automountlocation-find         Search for an automount location.
automountlocation-import       Import automount files for a specific location.
automountlocation-show         Display an automount location.
automountlocation-tofiles      Generate automount files for a specific location.
automountmap-add               Create a new automount map.
automountmap-add-indirect      Create a new indirect mount point.
automountmap-del               Delete an automount map.
automountmap-find              Search for an automount map.
automountmap-mod               Modify an automount map.
automountmap-show              Display an automount map.
cert-remove-hold               Take a revoked certificate off hold.
cert-request                   Submit a certificate signing request.
cert-revoke                    Revoke a certificate.
cert-show                      Retrieve an existing certificate.
cert-status                    Check the status of a certificate signing request.
config-mod                     Modify configuration options.
config-show                    Show the current configuration.
console                        Start the IPA interactive Python console.
delegation-add                 Add a new delegation.
delegation-del                 Delete a delegation.
delegation-find                Search for delegations.
delegation-mod                 Modify a delegation.
delegation-show                Display information about a delegation.
dns-resolve                    Resolve a host name in DNS
dnsrecord-add                  Add new DNS resource record.
dnsrecord-del                  Delete DNS resource record.
dnsrecord-find                 Search for DNS resources.
dnsrecord-show                 Display DNS resource.
entitle-consume                Consume an entitlement
entitle-find                   Search for entitlement accounts.
entitle-get                    Retrieve the entitlement certs
entitle-import                 Import an entitlement certificate.
entitle-register               Register to the entitlement system
entitle-status                 Display current entitlements
entitle-sync                   Re-sync the local entitlement cache with the entitlement server
env                            Show environment variables
group-add                      Create a new group.
group-add-member               Add members to a group.
group-del                      Delete group.
group-detach                   Detach a managed group from a user
group-find                     Search for groups.
group-mod                      Modify a group.
group-remove-member            Remove members from a group.
group-show                     Display information about a named group.
hbacrule-add                   Create a new HBAC rule.
hbacrule-add-host              Add target hosts and hostgroups to an HBAC rule
hbacrule-add-service           Add services to an HBAC rule.
hbacrule-add-sourcehost        Add source hosts and hostgroups from a HBAC rule.
hbacrule-add-user              Add users and groups to an HBAC rule.
hbacrule-del                   Delete an HBAC rule.
hbacrule-disable               Disable an HBAC rule.
hbacrule-enable                Enable an HBAC rule.
hbacrule-find                  Search for HBAC rules.
hbacrule-mod                   Modify an HBAC rule.
hbacrule-remove-host           Remove target hosts and hostgroups from an HBAC rule.
hbacrule-remove-service        Remove service and service groups from an HBAC rule.
hbacrule-remove-sourcehost     Remove source hosts and hostgroups from an HBAC rule.
hbacrule-remove-user           Remove users and groups from an HBAC rule.
hbacrule-show                  Display the properties of an HBAC rule.
hbacsvc-add                    Add a new HBAC service.
hbacsvc-del                    Delete an existing HBAC service.
hbacsvc-find                   Search for HBAC services.
hbacsvc-mod                    Modify an HBAC service.
hbacsvc-show                   Display information about an HBAC service.
hbacsvcgroup-add               Add a new HBAC service group.
hbacsvcgroup-add-member        Add members to an HBAC service group.
hbacsvcgroup-del               Delete an HBAC service group.
hbacsvcgroup-find              Search for an HBAC service group.
hbacsvcgroup-mod               Modify an HBAC service group.
hbacsvcgroup-remove-member     Remove members from an HBAC service group.
hbacsvcgroup-show              Display information about an HBAC service group.
help                           Display help for a command or topic.
host-add                       Add a new host.
host-add-managedby             Add hosts that can manage this host.
host-del                       Delete a host.
host-disable                   Disable the Kerberos key, SSL certificate and all services of a host.
host-find                      Search for hosts.
host-mod                       Modify information about a host.
host-remove-managedby          Remove hosts that can manage this host.
host-show                      Display information about a host.
hostgroup-add                  Add a new hostgroup.
hostgroup-add-member           Add members to a hostgroup.
hostgroup-del                  Delete a hostgroup.
hostgroup-find                 Search for hostgroups.
hostgroup-mod                  Modify a hostgroup.
hostgroup-remove-member        Remove members from a hostgroup.
hostgroup-show                 Display information about a hostgroup.
krbtpolicy-mod                 Modify Kerberos ticket policy.
krbtpolicy-reset               Reset Kerberos ticket policy to the default values.
krbtpolicy-show                Display the current Kerberos ticket policy.
migrate-ds                     Migrate users and groups from DS to IPA.
netgroup-add                   Add a new netgroup.
netgroup-add-member            Add members to a netgroup.
netgroup-del                   Delete a netgroup.
netgroup-find                  Search for a netgroup.
netgroup-mod                   Modify a netgroup.
netgroup-remove-member         Remove members from a netgroup.
netgroup-show                  Display information about a netgroup.
passwd                         Set a user's password
permission-add                 Add a new permission.
permission-del                 Delete a permission.
permission-find                Search for permissions.
permission-mod                 Modify a permission.
permission-show                Display information about a permission.
ping                           ping a remote server
plugins                        Show all loaded plugins
privilege-add                  Add a new privilege.
privilege-add-permission       Add permissions to a privilege.
privilege-del                  Delete a privilege.
privilege-find                 Search for privileges.
privilege-mod                  Modify a privilege.
privilege-remove-permission    Remove permissions from a privilege.
privilege-show                 Display information about a privilege.
pwpolicy-add                   Add a new group password policy.
pwpolicy-del                   Delete a group password policy.
pwpolicy-find                  Search for group password policies.
pwpolicy-mod                   Modify a group password policy.
pwpolicy-show                  Display information about password policy.
role-add                       Add a new role.
role-add-member                Add members to a role.
role-add-privilege             Add privileges to a role.
role-del                       Delete a role.
role-find                      Search for roles.
role-mod                       Modify a role.
role-remove-member             Remove members from a role.
role-remove-privilege          Remove privileges from a role.
role-show                      Display information about a role.
selfservice-add                Add a new self-service permission.
selfservice-del                Delete a self-service permission.
selfservice-find               Search for a self-service permission.
selfservice-mod                Modify a self-service permission.
selfservice-show               Display information about a self-service permission.
service-add                    Add a new IPA new service.
service-add-host               Add hosts that can manage this service.
service-del                    Delete an IPA service.
service-disable                Disable the Kerberos key and SSL certificate of a service.
service-find                   Search for IPA services.
service-mod                    Modify an existing IPA service.
service-remove-host            Remove hosts that can manage this service.
service-show                   Display information about an IPA service.
show-mappings                  ipalib.cli.show_mappings
sudocmd-add                    Create new sudo command.
sudocmd-del                    Delete sudo command.
sudocmd-find                   Search for commands.
sudocmd-mod                    Modify command.
sudocmd-show                   Display sudo command.
sudocmdgroup-add               Create new sudo command group.
sudocmdgroup-add-member        Add members to sudo command group.
sudocmdgroup-del               Delete sudo command group.
sudocmdgroup-find              Search for sudo command groups.
sudocmdgroup-mod               Modify group.
sudocmdgroup-remove-member     Remove members from sudo command group.
sudocmdgroup-show              Display sudo command group.
sudorule-add                   Create new Sudo Rule.
sudorule-add-allow-command     Add commands and sudo command groups affected by Sudo Rule.
sudorule-add-deny-command      Add commands and sudo command groups affected by Sudo Rule.
sudorule-add-host              Add hosts and hostgroups affected by Sudo Rule.
sudorule-add-option            Add an option to the Sudo rule.
sudorule-add-runasgroup        Add group for Sudo to execute as.
sudorule-add-runasuser         Add user for Sudo to execute as.
sudorule-add-user              Add users and groups affected by Sudo Rule.
sudorule-del                   Delete Sudo Rule.
sudorule-disable               Disable a Sudo rule.
sudorule-enable                Enable a Sudo rule.
sudorule-find                  Search for Sudo Rule.
sudorule-mod                   Modify Sudo Rule.
sudorule-remove-allow-command  Remove commands and sudo command groups affected by Sudo Rule.
sudorule-remove-deny-command   Remove commands and sudo command groups affected by Sudo Rule.
sudorule-remove-host           Remove hosts and hostgroups affected by Sudo Rule.
sudorule-remove-option         Remove an option from Sudo rule.
sudorule-remove-runasgroup     Remove group for Sudo to execute as.
sudorule-remove-runasuser      Remove user for Sudo to execute as.
sudorule-remove-user           Remove users and groups affected by Sudo Rule.
sudorule-show                  Dispaly Sudo Rule.
user-add                       Add a new user.
user-del                       Delete a user.
user-disable                   Disable a user account.
user-enable                    Enable a user account.
user-find                      Search for users.
user-mod                       Modify a user.
user-show                      Display information about a user.
user-unlock                    Unlock a user account
									
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Location
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</informaltable>
			</section>

				<section id="ipa-command-automount" condition="reviewing"><title>ipa automountlocation*</title>
					<para>
						info
					</para>
					

					<section id="ipa-automount-syntax"><title>Syntax</title>
						<cmdsynopsis>
							<command>ipa</command>
							<arg choice="plain">
								<replaceable>commands</replaceable>
							</arg>
							<arg choice="opt">
								<replaceable>options</replaceable>
							</arg>
						</cmdsynopsis>
					</section>

					<section id="ipa-automount-commands"><title>Commands</title>
						<informaltable>
							<tgroup cols="2">
								<thead>
									<row>
										<entry>
											Command
										</entry>
										<entry>
											Description
										</entry>
									</row>
								</thead>
								<tbody>
									<row>
										<entry>

automountkey-add               Create a new automount key.
automountkey-del               Delete an automount key.
automountkey-find              Search for an automount key.
automountkey-mod               Modify an automount key.
automountkey-show              Display an automount key.
automountlocation-add          Create a new automount location.
automountlocation-del          Delete an automount location.
automountlocation-find         Search for an automount location.
automountlocation-import       Import automount files for a specific location.
automountlocation-show         Display an automount location.
automountlocation-tofiles      Generate automount files for a specific location.
automountmap-add               Create a new automount map.
automountmap-add-indirect      Create a new indirect mount point.
automountmap-del               Delete an automount map.
automountmap-find              Search for an automount map.
automountmap-mod               Modify an automount map.
automountmap-show              Display an automount map.

									
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Location
									</entry>
								</row>
							</tbody>
						</tgroup>
					</informaltable>
				</section>
						
				<section id="ipa-automount-options"><title>Options</title>
					<informaltable>
						<tgroup cols="2">
							<thead>
								<row>
									<entry>
										Parameter
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Description
									</entry>
								</row>
							</thead>
							<tbody>
								<row>
									<entry>
  -h, --help         show this help message and exit
  -e KEY=VAL         Set environment variable KEY to VAL
  -c FILE            Load configuration from FILE
  -d, --debug        Produce full debuging output
  -v, --verbose      Produce more verbose output. A second -v displays the
                     XML-RPC request
  -a, --prompt-all   Prompt for ALL values (even if optional)
  -n, --no-prompt    Prompt for NO values (even if required)
  -f, --no-fallback  Only use the server configured in /etc/ipa/default.conf
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Location
									</entry>
								</row>
							</tbody>
						</tgroup>
					</informaltable>
				</section>
			</section>

				<section id="ipa-command-automountmap" condition="reviewing"><title>ipa automountmap*</title>
					<para>
						info
					</para>
					

					<section id="ipa-automountmap-syntax"><title>Syntax</title>
						<cmdsynopsis>
							<command>ipa</command>
							<arg choice="plain">
								<replaceable>commands</replaceable>
							</arg>
							<arg choice="opt">
								<replaceable>options</replaceable>
							</arg>
						</cmdsynopsis>
					</section>

					<section id="ipa-automountmap-commands"><title>Commands</title>
						<informaltable>
							<tgroup cols="2">
								<thead>
									<row>
										<entry>
											Command
										</entry>
										<entry>
											Description
										</entry>
									</row>
								</thead>
								<tbody>
									<row>
										<entry>

automountkey-add               Create a new automount key.
automountkey-del               Delete an automount key.
automountkey-find              Search for an automount key.
automountkey-mod               Modify an automount key.
automountkey-show              Display an automount key.
automountlocation-add          Create a new automount location.
automountlocation-del          Delete an automount location.
automountlocation-find         Search for an automount location.
automountlocation-import       Import automount files for a specific location.
automountlocation-show         Display an automount location.
automountlocation-tofiles      Generate automount files for a specific location.
automountmap-add               Create a new automount map.
automountmap-add-indirect      Create a new indirect mount point.
automountmap-del               Delete an automount map.
automountmap-find              Search for an automount map.
automountmap-mod               Modify an automount map.
automountmap-show              Display an automount map.

									
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Location
									</entry>
								</row>
							</tbody>
						</tgroup>
					</informaltable>
				</section>
						
				<section id="ipa-automountmap-options"><title>Options</title>
					<informaltable>
						<tgroup cols="2">
							<thead>
								<row>
									<entry>
										Parameter
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Description
									</entry>
								</row>
							</thead>
							<tbody>
								<row>
									<entry>
  -h, --help         show this help message and exit
  -e KEY=VAL         Set environment variable KEY to VAL
  -c FILE            Load configuration from FILE
  -d, --debug        Produce full debuging output
  -v, --verbose      Produce more verbose output. A second -v displays the
                     XML-RPC request
  -a, --prompt-all   Prompt for ALL values (even if optional)
  -n, --no-prompt    Prompt for NO values (even if required)
  -f, --no-fallback  Only use the server configured in /etc/ipa/default.conf
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Location
									</entry>
								</row>
							</tbody>
						</tgroup>
					</informaltable>
				</section>
			</section>

				<section id="ipa-command-automountkey" condition="reviewing"><title>ipa automountkey*</title>
					<para>
						info
					</para>
					

					<section id="ipa-automountkey-syntax"><title>Syntax</title>
						<cmdsynopsis>
							<command>ipa</command>
							<arg choice="plain">
								<replaceable>commands</replaceable>
							</arg>
							<arg choice="opt">
								<replaceable>options</replaceable>
							</arg>
						</cmdsynopsis>
					</section>

					<section id="ipa-automountkey-commands"><title>Commands</title>
						<informaltable>
							<tgroup cols="2">
								<thead>
									<row>
										<entry>
											Command
										</entry>
										<entry>
											Description
										</entry>
									</row>
								</thead>
								<tbody>
									<row>
										<entry>

automountkey-add               Create a new automount key.
automountkey-del               Delete an automount key.
automountkey-find              Search for an automount key.
automountkey-mod               Modify an automount key.
automountkey-show              Display an automount key.
automountlocation-add          Create a new automount location.
automountlocation-del          Delete an automount location.
automountlocation-find         Search for an automount location.
automountlocation-import       Import automount files for a specific location.
automountlocation-show         Display an automount location.
automountlocation-tofiles      Generate automount files for a specific location.
automountmap-add               Create a new automount map.
automountmap-add-indirect      Create a new indirect mount point.
automountmap-del               Delete an automount map.
automountmap-find              Search for an automount map.
automountmap-mod               Modify an automount map.
automountmap-show              Display an automount map.

									
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Location
									</entry>
								</row>
							</tbody>
						</tgroup>
					</informaltable>
				</section>
						
				<section id="ipa-automountkey-options"><title>Options</title>
					<informaltable>
						<tgroup cols="2">
							<thead>
								<row>
									<entry>
										Parameter
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Description
									</entry>
								</row>
							</thead>
							<tbody>
								<row>
									<entry>
  -h, --help         show this help message and exit
  -e KEY=VAL         Set environment variable KEY to VAL
  -c FILE            Load configuration from FILE
  -d, --debug        Produce full debuging output
  -v, --verbose      Produce more verbose output. A second -v displays the
                     XML-RPC request
  -a, --prompt-all   Prompt for ALL values (even if optional)
  -n, --no-prompt    Prompt for NO values (even if required)
  -f, --no-fallback  Only use the server configured in /etc/ipa/default.conf
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Location
									</entry>
								</row>
							</tbody>
						</tgroup>
					</informaltable>
				</section>			
			</section>
		</section>

		<section id="ipa-dns"><title>ipa DNS Commands</title>
			<para>
				There are a collection of commands used to add and manage DNS zones and DNS records.
			</para>	

				<section id="ipa-command-dnszone-add"><title>ipa dnszone-add</title>
					<para>
						Creates a new DNS zone in the &IPA; server.
					</para>
					

					<section id="ipa-dnszone-add-syntax"><title>Syntax</title>
						<cmdsynopsis>
							<command>ipa dnszone-add</command>
								<arg choice="plain">
									<replaceable>zoneName</replaceable>
								</arg>
								<arg choice="opt">
									--name-server=<replaceable>name</replaceable>
							</arg>

								<arg choice="opt">
									--ip-address=<replaceable>IPaddress</replaceable>
								</arg>
								<arg choice="opt">
									--name-from-ip=<replaceable>IPaddress</replaceable>
								</arg>
								
								<arg choice="opt">
									--admin-email=<replaceable>email</replaceable>
								</arg>
								
								<arg choice="opt">
									--serial=<replaceable>#</replaceable>
								</arg>
								
								<arg choice="opt">
									--refresh=<replaceable>#</replaceable>
								</arg>
								
								<arg choice="opt">
									--retry=<replaceable>#</replaceable>
								</arg>
								
								<arg choice="opt">
									--expire=<replaceable>#</replaceable>
								</arg>
								
								<arg choice="opt">
									--minimum=<replaceable>#</replaceable>
								</arg>
								
								<arg choice="opt">
									--ttl=<replaceable>#</replaceable>
								</arg>
								
								<arg choice="opt">
									--class=<replaceable>name</replaceable>
								</arg>
								<arg choice="opt">
									--update-policy=<replaceable>string</replaceable>
								</arg>
								<arg choice="opt">
									--dynamic-update=TRUE|FALSE
								</arg>
								<arg choice="opt">
									--allow-query=<replaceable>string</replaceable>
								</arg>
								<arg choice="opt">
									--allow-transfer=<replaceable>string</replaceable>
								</arg>
								<arg choice="opt">
									--allow-sync-ptr=TRUE|FALSE
								</arg>
								<arg choice="opt">
									--forwarder=<replaceable>string</replaceable>
								</arg>
								<arg choice="opt">
									--forward-policy=only|first
								</arg>
								<arg choice="opt">
									--force
								</arg>
						</cmdsynopsis>
					</section>
						
				<section id="ipa-dnszone-add-options"><title>Options</title>
					<informaltable>
						<tgroup cols="2">
							<thead>
								<row>
									<entry>
										Parameter
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Description
									</entry>
								</row>
							</thead>
							<tbody>
								
								<row><entry> 
									<emphasis>zoneName</emphasis>
								</entry><entry>Sets the name of the new zone. This is required.</entry></row>
								<row><entry>
									--name-server=<emphasis>name</emphasis>
							</entry><entry>Gives the name of the authoritative DNS server to use, based on the hostname.</entry></row>

								<row><entry>
									--ip-address=<emphasis>IPaddress</emphasis>
								</entry><entry>Sets a DNS name server to use with the &IPA; domain, based on the IP address.</entry></row>
								<row><entry>
									--name-from-ip=<emphasis>IPaddress</emphasis>
								</entry><entry>Gives an IP address for the DNS zone to use to create a reverse zone name.</entry></row>
								
								<row><entry>
									--admin-email=<emphasis>email</emphasis>
								</entry><entry>Gives the email address of the DNS domain administrator.</entry></row>
								
								<row><entry>
									--serial=<emphasis>#</emphasis>
								</entry><entry>Sets the serial number to use for the DNS start of authority (SOA) record.</entry></row>
								
								<row><entry>
									--refresh=<emphasis>#</emphasis>
								</entry><entry>Sets the time interval to use to check for updated SOA records.</entry></row>
								
								<row><entry>
									--retry=<emphasis>#</emphasis>
								</entry><entry>Sets the time to wait before retrying a failed name resolution attempt.</entry></row>
								
								<row><entry>
									--expire=<emphasis>#</emphasis>
								</entry><entry>Sets the time to hold successful resolution attempts in the cache before they expire.</entry></row>
								
								<row><entry>
									--minimum=<emphasis>#</emphasis>
								</entry><entry>Sets the time to hold negative or failed resolution attempts in the cache.</entry></row>
								
								<row><entry>
									--ttl=<emphasis>#</emphasis>
								</entry><entry>Sets how long to hold SOA records in the cache.</entry></row>
								
								<row><entry>
									--class=<emphasis>name</emphasis>
								</entry><entry>Sets a SOA record class for zone entries.</entry></row>
								<row><entry>
									--update-policy=<emphasis>string</emphasis>
								</entry><entry>Sets a BIND service policy.</entry></row>
								<row><entry>
									--dynamic-update=TRUE|FALSE
								</entry><entry>Enables domain clients to update their own DNS entries dynamically.</entry></row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--allow-query=<replaceable>string</replaceable>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Gives a semi-colon-separated listed of IP addresses or network names which are allowed to issue DNS queries.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--allow-transfer=<replaceable>string</replaceable>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Gives a semi-colon-separated listed of IP addresses or network names which are allowed to transfer the given zone.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--allow-sync-ptr=TRUE|FALSE
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Sets whether A or AAAA records (forward records) for the zone will be automatically synchronized with the PTR (reverse) records.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--forwarder=<replaceable>string</replaceable>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Specifies a forwarder specifically configured for the DNS zone. This is separate from any global forwarders used in the &IPA; domain.
										<para>
											To specify multiple forwarders, use the option multiple times.
										</para>
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--forward-policy=only|first
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Sets whether the zone will only forward requests to configured the DNS name servers (a <emphasis>forward-only</emphasis> zone) or whether it will check the forwarders first for DNS records and then check its own local records.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row><entry>
									--force
								</entry><entry>Forces a zone to be created in the &IPA; configuration even if the name server is not recognized by the DNS.</entry></row>
							</tbody>
						</tgroup>
					</informaltable>
				</section>			
			</section>

				<section id="ipa-command-dnsrecord-add"><title>ipa dnsrecord-add</title>
					<para>
						Adds a new resource record.
					</para>
					<para>
						Each resource record type has its own set of options, based on the required information to configure the record.
					</para>
					

					<section id="ipa-dnsrecord-syntax"><title>Syntax</title>
						<cmdsynopsis>
							<command>ipa dnsrecord-add</command>
							<arg choice="plain">
									<replaceable>zoneName</replaceable>
								</arg>
							<arg choice="plain">
									<replaceable>recordName</replaceable>
								</arg>
								<arg choice="opt">
									--<replaceable>recordType_options=value</replaceable>
								</arg>
						</cmdsynopsis>
					</section>

						
				<section id="ipa-dnsrecord-options"><title>Options</title>
					<informaltable>
						<tgroup cols="2">
							<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" />
							<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" />
							<thead>
								<row>
									<entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">
										General Record Options
									</entry>
								</row>
							</thead>
							<tbody>
								<row>
									<entry>
										<emphasis role="bold">Option</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										<emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--ttl=<emphasis>number</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Sets the time to live for the record. 
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--class=IN | CS | CH | HS
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Sets the class of the record. This is usually IN, for Internet protocol.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--structured
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Parses the raw DNS records and returns them in a structured format.
									</entry>
								</row>
							</tbody>
						</tgroup>
						<tgroup cols="2">
							<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" />
							<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" />
							<thead>
								<row>
									<entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">
										"A" Record Options
									</entry>
								</row>
							</thead>
							<tbody>
								<row>
									<entry>
										<emphasis role="bold">Option</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										<emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--a-rec=<emphasis>ARECORD</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Passes a comma-separated list of A records. 
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--a-ip-address=<emphasis>string</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Gives the IP address for the record.
									</entry>
								</row>
							</tbody>
						</tgroup>
						<tgroup cols="2">
							<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" />
							<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" />
							<thead>
								<row>
									<entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">
										"A6" Record Options
									</entry>
								</row>
							</thead>
							<tbody>
								<row>
									<entry>
										<emphasis role="bold">Option</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										<emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--a6-rec=<emphasis>A6RECORD</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Passes a comma-separated list of A6 records. 
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--a6-data=<emphasis>string</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Gives the data for the record.
									</entry>
								</row>
							</tbody>
						</tgroup>

						
						<tgroup cols="2">
							<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" />
							<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" />
							<thead>
								<row>
									<entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">
										"AAAA" Record Options
									</entry>
								</row>
							</thead>
							<tbody>
								<row>
									<entry>
										<emphasis role="bold">Option</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										<emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--aaaa-rec=<emphasis>AAAARECORD</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Passes a comma-separated list of AAAA (IPv6) records. 
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--aaaa-ip-address=<emphasis>string</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Gives the IPv6 address for the record.
									</entry>
								</row>
							</tbody>
						</tgroup>

						
						<tgroup cols="2">
							<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" />
							<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" />
							<thead>
								<row>
									<entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">
										"AFSDB" Record Options
									</entry>
								</row>
							</thead>
							<tbody>
								<row>
									<entry>
										<emphasis role="bold">Option</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										<emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--afsdb-rec=<emphasis>AFSDBRECORD</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Passes a comma-separated list of AFSDB records. 
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--afsdb-subtype=1 | 2
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Gives the subtype of the AFS database.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--afsdb-hostname=<emphasis>string</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Gives the hostname of the AFS database.
									</entry>
								</row>
							</tbody>
						</tgroup>
						

						
						<tgroup cols="2">
							<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" />
							<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" />
							<thead>
								<row>
									<entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">
										"CERT" Record Options
									</entry>
								</row>
							</thead>
							<tbody>
								<row>
									<entry>
										<emphasis role="bold">Option</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										<emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--cert-rec=<emphasis>CERTRECORD</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Passes a comma-separated list of CERT records. 
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--cert-type=<emphasis>number</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Gives the type of certificate. Common values include 1 (X.509 certificate), 3 (PGP packet), 4 (URL of an X.509 certificate), and 254 (private OID).
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--cert-key-tag=<emphasis>number</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Contains a 16-bit computed value that represents the certificate key. This is generated based on the given key algorithm in the certificate.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--cert-algorithm=<emphasis>number</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Contains the algorithm used to create the public key.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--cert-certificate-or-crl=<emphasis>number</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Contains the base 64-encoded blob of the X.509 object (certificate or CRL).
									</entry>
								</row>
							</tbody>
						</tgroup>

						
						<tgroup cols="2">
							<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" />
							<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" />
							<thead>
								<row>
									<entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">
										"CNAME" Record Options
									</entry>
								</row>
							</thead>
							<tbody>
								<row>
									<entry>
										<emphasis role="bold">Option</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										<emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--cname-rec=<emphasis>CNAMERECORD</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Passes a comma-separated list of CNAME records. 
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--cname-hostname=<emphasis>string</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Gives the real hostname that the CNAME alias hostname points to.
									</entry>
								</row>
							</tbody>
						</tgroup>

						
						<tgroup cols="2">
							<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" />
							<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" />
							<thead>
								<row>
									<entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">
										"DNAME" Record Options
									</entry>
								</row>
							</thead>
							<tbody>
								<row>
									<entry>
										<emphasis role="bold">Option</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										<emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--dname-rec=<emphasis>DNAMERECORD</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Passes a comma-separated list of DNAME records. 
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--dname-target=<emphasis>string</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Gives the domain name of the target DNS domain.
									</entry>
								</row>
							</tbody>
						</tgroup>

						
						<tgroup cols="2">
							<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" />
							<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" />
							<thead>
								<row>
									<entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">
										"DS" Record Options
									</entry>
								</row>
							</thead>
							<tbody>
								<row>
									<entry>
										<emphasis role="bold">Option</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										<emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--ds-rec=<emphasis>DSRECORD</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Passes a comma-separated list of DNSSEC key records. 
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--ds-key-tag=<emphasis>number</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Contains a 16-bit computed value that represents the certificate key. This is generated based on the given key algorithm.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--ds-algorithm=<emphasis>number</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Contains the algorithm used to create the public key.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--ds-digest-type=<emphasis>number</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Contains the algorithm used to create the digest. This is 1, for SHA-1.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--ds-digest=<emphasis>string</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Contains the digest for the DNSKEY. This is calculated by combining the fully qualified owner name of the DNSKEY resource record, the DNSKEY data, and the digest algorithm.
									</entry>
								</row>
							</tbody>
						</tgroup>

						
						<tgroup cols="2">
							<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" />
							<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" />
							<thead>
								<row>
									<entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">
										"KEY" Record Options
									</entry>
								</row>
							</thead>
							<tbody>
								<row>
									<entry>
										<emphasis role="bold">Option</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										<emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--key-rec=<emphasis>KEYRECORD</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Passes a comma-separated list of KEY records. 
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--key-flags=<emphasis>number</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Gives a series of bits the indicate aspects of the key. Bits 0-1 show  key usage, bits 6-7 show the key entity type (such as a user or account), and bits 12-15 show the key signature settings. For more information, see <ulink url="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc2535#section-3" />.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--key-protocol=<emphasis>number</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Shows what Internet protocols the key can be used with. This value can be 1 (TLS), 2 (email), 3 (DNSSEC), 4 (IPSEC), or 255 (all).
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--key-algorithm=<emphasis>number</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Contains the algorithm used to create the key.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--key-public-key=<emphasis>number</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Contains the public key.
									</entry>
								</row>
							</tbody>
						</tgroup>

						
						<tgroup cols="2">
							<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" />
							<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" />
							<thead>
								<row>
									<entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">
										"KX" Record Options
									</entry>
								</row>
							</thead>
							<tbody>
								<row>
									<entry>
										<emphasis role="bold">Option</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										<emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--kx-rec=<emphasis>KXRECORD</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Passes a comma-separated list of KX records. 
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--kx-preference=<emphasis>number</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Sets the priority of the specified key exchanger. The lower the number, the higher priority.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--kx-exchanger=<emphasis>string</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Gives the hostname of a server which can act as a key exchanger.
									</entry>
								</row>
							</tbody>
						</tgroup>


						
						<tgroup cols="2">
							<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" />
							<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" />
							<thead>
								<row>
									<entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">
										"LOC" Record Options
									</entry>
								</row>
							</thead>
							<tbody>
								<row>
									<entry>
										<emphasis role="bold">Option</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										<emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--loc-rec=<emphasis>LOCRECORD</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Passes a comma-separated list of location information records. 
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--loc-lat-deg=<emphasis>number</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Gives the degrees element of the latitude of the physical location of a network object.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--loc-lat-min=<emphasis>number</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Gives the minutes element of the latitude of the physical location of a network object.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--loc-lat-sec=<emphasis>decimal</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Gives the seconds element of the latitude of the physical location of a network object.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--loc-lat-dir=N | S
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Gives the hemisphere (north or south) of the latitude.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--loc-lon-deg=<emphasis>number</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Gives the degrees element of the longitude of the physical location of a network object.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--loc-lon-min=<emphasis>number</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Gives the minutes element of the longitude of the physical location of a network object.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--loc-lon-sec=<emphasis>decimal</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Gives the seconds element of the longitude of the physical location of a network object.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--loc-lon-dir=E | W
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Gives the orientation or direction (east or west) of the longitude.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--loc-altitude=<emphasis>decimal</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Gives the altitude of the physical location of a network object.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--loc-size=<emphasis>decimal</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Gives the diameter of a circle encompassing the object, to give an idea of its physical size.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--loc-h-precision=<emphasis>decimal</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Gives the diameter of a circle which constitutes the margin of error for estimating the physical size of the object.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--loc-v-precision=<emphasis>decimal</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Gives the diameter of a circle which constitutes the margin of error for estimating the altitude of the object.
									</entry>
								</row>
							</tbody>
						</tgroup>

						
						<tgroup cols="2">
							<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" />
							<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" />
							<thead>
								<row>
									<entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">
										"MX" Record Options
									</entry>
								</row>
							</thead>
							<tbody>
								<row>
									<entry>
										<emphasis role="bold">Option</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										<emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--mx-rec=<emphasis>MXRECORD</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Passes a comma-separated list of MX records. 
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--mx-preference=<emphasis>number</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Sets the priority of the specified mail server. The lower the number, the higher priority.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--mx-exchanger=<emphasis>string</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Gives the hostname of a mail server.
									</entry>
								</row>
							</tbody>
						</tgroup>

						
						<tgroup cols="2">
							<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" />
							<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" />
							<thead>
								<row>
									<entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">
										"NAPTR" Record Options
									</entry>
								</row>
							</thead>
							<tbody>
								<row>
									<entry>
										<emphasis role="bold">Option</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										<emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--naptr-rec=<emphasis>NAPTRRECORD</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Passes a comma-separated list of pointer records. 
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--naptr-order=<emphasis>number</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Contains a 16-bit unsigned number which sets that order to use to process naming authority pointer records.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--napter-preference=<emphasis>number</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Contains a 16-bit unsigned number which is the secondary method used to determine the weight or priority of naming authority pointer records with the same order value.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--napter-flags=<emphasis>string</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Contains an application-specific series of characters which sets how to manage field values.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--napter-service=<emphasis>string</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Contains application-specific values which are used to configure the NAPTR service.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--napter-regexp=<emphasis>string</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Contains a substitution expression  which is used to help look up the next domain name in the queue.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--napter-replacement=<emphasis>string</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Contains a fully-qualified domain name to use with <option>--napter-regexp</option> if the expression is a simple replacement.
									</entry>
								</row>
							</tbody>
						</tgroup>

						
						<tgroup cols="2">
							<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" />
							<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" />
							<thead>
								<row>
									<entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">
										"NS" Record Options
									</entry>
								</row>
							</thead>
							<tbody>
								<row>
									<entry>
										<emphasis role="bold">Option</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										<emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--ns-rec=<emphasis>NSRECORD</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Passes a comma-separated list of NS records. 
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--ns-hostname=<emphasis>string</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Gives the hostname of the authoritative name server.
									</entry>
								</row>
							</tbody>
						</tgroup>

						
						<tgroup cols="2">
							<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" />
							<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" />
							<thead>
								<row>
									<entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">
										"NSEC" Record Options
									</entry>
								</row>
							</thead>
							<tbody>
								<row>
									<entry>
										<emphasis role="bold">Option</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										<emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--nsec-rec=<emphasis>NSECRECORD</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Passes a comma-separated list of NSEC key records. 
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--nsec-next=<emphasis>string</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Gives the next domain name in the canonical order of the DNS zone.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
									--nsec-types=<emphasis>types</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Contains a list of record types supported in the domain. The types can be SOA, A, AAAA, A6, AFSDB, APL, CERT, CNAME, DHCID, DLV, DNAME, DNSKEY, DS, HIP, IPSECKEY, KEY, KX, LOC, MX, NAPTR, NS, NSEC, NSEC3, NSEC3PARAM, PTR, RRSIG, RP, SIG, SPF, SRV, SSHFP, TA, TKEY, TSIG, TXT.
									</entry>
								</row>
							</tbody>
						</tgroup>
						
						<tgroup cols="2">
							<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" />
							<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" />
							<thead>
								<row>
									<entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">
										"PTR" Record Options
									</entry>
								</row>
							</thead>
							<tbody>
								<row>
									<entry>
										<emphasis role="bold">Option</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										<emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--ptr-rec=<emphasis>PTRRECORD</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Passes a comma-separated list of PTR records. 
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--ptr-hostname=<emphasis>string</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Gives the hostname for the record.
									</entry>
								</row>
							</tbody>
						</tgroup>

						
						<tgroup cols="2">
							<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" />
							<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" />
							<thead>
								<row>
									<entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">
										"RRSIG" Record Options
									</entry>
								</row>
							</thead>
							<tbody>
								<row>
									<entry>
										<emphasis role="bold">Option</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										<emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--rrsig-rec=<emphasis>RRSIGRECORD</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Passes a comma-separated list of RRSIG key records. 
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--rrsig-algorithm=<emphasis>number</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Contains the algorithm used to sign the resource record set.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--rrsig-key-tag=<emphasis>number</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Contains a 16-bit computed value that represents the key used to sign the resource record set.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--rrsig-labels=<emphasis>number</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Gives the number of labels in the owner name; this is used to validate the signature.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
									--rrsig-type-covered=<emphasis>types</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Identified what resource record type is covered in the specific RRSIG set. The types can be SOA, A, AAAA, A6, AFSDB, APL, CERT, CNAME, DHCID, DLV, DNAME, DNSKEY, DS, HIP, IPSECKEY, KEY, KX, LOC, MX, NAPTR, NS, NSEC, NSEC3, NSEC3PARAM, PTR, RRSIG, RP, SIG, SPF, SRV, SSHFP, TA, TKEY, TSIG, TXT.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--rrsig-original-ttl=<emphasis>number</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Gives the time-to-live of the records set in the authoritative zone.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--rrsig-signature-inception=<emphasis>string</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Gives the beginning date of the record set's validity period.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--rrsig-signature-expiration=<emphasis>string</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Gives the end date of the record set's validity period.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--rrsig-signers-name=<emphasis>string</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Gives the name of the signer of the DNSKEY for the record set. This must include the name of the zone.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--rrsig-signature=<emphasis>string</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Contains the digital signature for the record set.
									</entry>
								</row>
							</tbody>
						</tgroup>
						
						<tgroup cols="2">
							<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" />
							<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" />
							<thead>
								<row>
									<entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">
										"SIG" Record Options
									</entry>
								</row>
							</thead>
							<tbody>
								<row>
									<entry>
										<emphasis role="bold">Option</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										<emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--sig-rec=<emphasis>SIGRECORD</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Passes a comma-separated list of SIG key records. 
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--sig-algorithm=<emphasis>number</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Contains the algorithm used to sign the resource record set.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--sig-key-tag=<emphasis>number</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Contains a 16-bit computed value that represents the key used to sign the resource record set.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--sig-labels=<emphasis>number</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Gives the number of labels in the owner name; this is used to validate the signature.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
									--sig-type-covered=<emphasis>types</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Identified what resource record type is covered in the specific RRSIG set. The types can be SOA, A, AAAA, A6, AFSDB, APL, CERT, CNAME, DHCID, DLV, DNAME, DNSKEY, DS, HIP, IPSECKEY, KEY, KX, LOC, MX, NAPTR, NS, NSEC, NSEC3, NSEC3PARAM, PTR, RRSIG, RP, SIG, SPF, SRV, SSHFP, TA, TKEY, TSIG, TXT.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--sig-original-ttl=<emphasis>number</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Gives the time-to-live of the records set in the authoritative zone.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--sig-signature-inception=<emphasis>string</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Gives the beginning date of the record set's validity period.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--sig-signature-expiration=<emphasis>string</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Gives the end date of the record set's validity period.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--sig-signers-name=<emphasis>string</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Gives the name of the signer of the DNSKEY for the record set. This must include the name of the zone.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--sig-signature=<emphasis>string</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Contains the digital signature for the record set.
									</entry>
								</row>
							</tbody>
						</tgroup>

						<tgroup cols="2">
							<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" />
							<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" />
							<thead>
								<row>
									<entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">
										"SRV" Record Options
									</entry>
								</row>
							</thead>
							<tbody>
								<row>
									<entry>
										<emphasis role="bold">Option</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										<emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--srv-rec=<emphasis>SRVRECORD</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Passes a comma-separated list of SRV records. 
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--srv-priority=<emphasis>number</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Sets the priority of the record. There can be multiple SRV records for a service type. The priority (0 - 65535) sets the rank of the record; the lower the number, the higher the priority. A service has to use the record with the highest priority first.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--srv-weight=<emphasis>number</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Sets the weight of the record. This helps determine the order of SRV records with the same priority.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--srv-port=<emphasis>number</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Gives the port for the service on the target host.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--srv-target=<emphasis>string</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Gives the domain name of the target host. This can be a single period (.) if the service is not available in the domain.
									</entry>
								</row>
							</tbody>
						</tgroup>
						
						<tgroup cols="2">
							<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" />
							<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" />
							<thead>
								<row>
									<entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">
										"SSHFP" Record Options
									</entry>
								</row>
							</thead>
							<tbody>
								<row>
									<entry>
										<emphasis role="bold">Option</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										<emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--sshfp-rec=<emphasis>SSHFPRECORD</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Passes a comma-separated list of SSH fingerprint records. 
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--sshfp-algorithm=<emphasis>number</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Contains the algorithm used for the SSH fingerprint.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--sshfp-fp-type=1
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Identifies the type of fingerprint. This value is always 1, for SHA-1.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--sshfp-fingerprint=<emphasis>string</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Contains the fingerprint, as calculated from the public key.
									</entry>
								</row>
							</tbody>
						</tgroup>
						<tgroup cols="2">
							<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" />
							<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" />
							<thead>
								<row>
									<entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">
										"TXT" Record Options
									</entry>
								</row>
							</thead>
							<tbody>
								<row>
									<entry>
										<emphasis role="bold">Option</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										<emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--txt-rec=<emphasis>TXTRECORD</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Passes a comma-separated list of TXT records. 
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>
										--txt-data=<emphasis>string</emphasis>
									</entry>
									<entry>
										Gives text data for the record.
									</entry>
								</row>
							</tbody>
						</tgroup>
					</informaltable>
				</section>			
			</section>
		</section>

		<section id="ipa-command-host"><title>ipa Host Commands</title>
					<para>
						This is a collection of subcommands which manage the client, or host, configuration within the &IPA; domain.
					</para>
					
				<section id="ipa-host-add"><title>ipa host-add</title>
					<para>
						Adds a new &IPA; client machine to the domain manually. This is done as part of the enrollment process.
					</para>
					<section id="ipa-host-add-syntax"><title>Syntax</title>
						<cmdsynopsis>
							<command>ipa host-add</command>
							<arg choice="plain">
								<replaceable>hostname</replaceable>
							</arg>
							<arg choice="opt">
								--desc="<replaceable>description</replaceable>"
							</arg>
							
							<arg choice="opt">
								--locality="<replaceable>cityName</replaceable>"
							</arg>
							<arg choice="opt">
								--location="<replaceable>location</replaceable>"
							</arg>
							<arg choice="opt">
								--platform="<replaceable>hardware_description</replaceable>"
							</arg>
							<arg choice="opt">
								--os="<replaceable>OS_version</replaceable>"
							</arg>
							<arg choice="opt">
								--password="<replaceable>enrollment_password</replaceable>"
							</arg>
							<arg choice="opt">
								--random
							</arg>
							<arg choice="opt">
								--certificate="<replaceable>base64_cert</replaceable>"
							</arg>
							<arg choice="opt">
								--force
							</arg>
							<arg choice="opt">
								--no-reverse
							</arg>
							<arg choice="opt">
								--ip-address=<replaceable>IPaddress</replaceable>
							</arg>
						</cmdsynopsis>
					</section>

					<section id="ipa-host-add-options"><title>Options</title>
						<informaltable>
							<tgroup cols="2">
								<thead>
									<row>
										<entry>
											Command
										</entry>
										<entry>
											Description
										</entry>
									</row>
								</thead>
								<tbody>
							<row><entry> choice="plain">
								<emphasis>hostname</emphasis>
						</entry><entry>Sets the name of the host entry to create, based on the fully-qualified domain name of the host.

							<important><title>IMPORTANT</title>
								<para>
									This must be a valid DNS name, which means only numbers, alphabetic characters, and hyphens (-) are allowed. Other characters, like underscores, in the hostname will cause DNS failures.
								</para>
							</important>
				</entry></row>
							<row><entry>
								--desc="<emphasis>description</emphasis>"
							</entry><entry>Gives a text description of the host.</entry></row>
							
							<row><entry>
								--locality="<emphasis>cityName</emphasis>"
							</entry><entry>Gives the geographical location, usually a city, where the host machine is.</entry></row>
							<row><entry>
								--location="<emphasis>location</emphasis>"
							</entry><entry>Gives the physical location, like a colocation facility, room number, or rack, where the host machine is.</entry></row>
							<row><entry>
								--platform="<emphasis>hardware_description</emphasis>"
							</entry><entry>Gives a hardware description of the host machine.</entry></row>
							<row><entry>
								--os="<emphasis>OS_version</emphasis>"
						</entry><entry>Gives the operating system type, such as <emphasis>"&OS; &OVER;"</emphasis>.</entry></row>
							<row><entry>
								--password="<emphasis>enrollment_password</emphasis>"
							</entry><entry>For a bulk enrollment, manually sets a password to use to proceed with the enrollment.</entry></row>
							<row><entry>
								--random
							</entry><entry>For a bulk enrollment, randomly generates a password to use to proceed with the enrollment.</entry></row>
							<row><entry>
								--certificate="<emphasis>base64_cert</emphasis>"
							</entry><entry>Contains the full base 64-encoded blob for a server certificate for the host.</entry></row>
							<row><entry>
								--force
							</entry><entry>Forces the server to create a host entry with the given name, even if the hostname cannot be resolved in DNS.</entry></row>
							<row><entry>
								--no-reverse
							</entry><entry>Disables reverse DNS creation through the server installation process. (If a reverse DNS zone is already configured, then that existing reverse DNS zone is used.) If this option is not used, then the default value is true, which assumes that reverse DNS should be configured by the installation script.</entry></row>
							<row><entry>
								--ip-address=<emphasis>IPaddress</emphasis>
							</entry><entry>Adds the host machine using its IP address, rather than the hostname.</entry></row>
							</tbody>
						</tgroup>
					</informaltable>
				</section>
			</section>

		</section>

	<section id="server-tools"><title>Server Scripts</title>
		<para>
			These are scripts that are used to manage the &IPA; server configuration. These scripts do not manage &IPA; domain entries; they manage the configuration of the server itself. This means that 
			these scripts are run as system administrative users rather than domain administrative users.
		</para>

		
			<section id="ipa-tool"><title>A Quick Summary of Configuration Scripts</title>
				<para>
					There are two basic categories of command-line scripts that &PROD; has available. 
				</para>
				<para>
					The first is a selection of independent configuration scripts which are used to set up machines that operate within the domain. 
				       	Most of these scripts are used to add servers and clients to the &IPA; domain, such as the <command>ipa-server-install</command>, 
					<command>ipa-client-install</command>, and <command>ipa-replica-install</command> scripts. 
				</para>
				<para>
					Some scripts are also available to enable services within the &IPA; server, such as adding CA services to a replica or enabling DNS. 
					Several services can be configured when a server or replica is installed, but few of those services are required. If a server is configured 
					without a service like DNS, that service can be enabled later using a specific configuration script, such as <command>ipa-dns-install</command>.
				</para>
				<para>
					Then there are scripts that are simply used to manage &IPA; domain. These scripts can be used to create or delete keytabs and certificates for any service or host within the domain, to set management rules for hosts and services (<emphasis>managed by</emphasis> settings), 
				</para>
				<para>
					Then there are a handful of scripts which are strictly internal, like <command>ipa-join</command>, meaning they are called by other management scripts but are not invoked by administrators directly.
				</para>
				<table id="tab.ipa-scripts"><title>&IPA; Scripts</title>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Name
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Description
								</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>
ipa-ca-install									
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Installs a Dogtag CA on a replica which previously did not have a CA installed.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									ipa-join
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Adds a client or host machine to the &IPA; domain. <emphasis>Used by other scripts; not invoked by administrators directly.</emphasis>
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									ipa-replica-prepare
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Pulls the configuration from &IPAA; server to use to set up a replica.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									ipa-client-install
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Sets up the host entry for a &OS; system and configures all associated services.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									ipa-ldap-updater
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Updates the &DSF; databases used by the &IPA; server. <emphasis>Used by other scripts; not invoked by administrators directly.</emphasis>
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									ipa-rmkeytab
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Deletes a keytab generated for &IPAA; user, service, or host.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									ipa-compat-manage
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Enables or disables the compatibility plug-in to use with NIS servers running with RFC 2307 schema.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									ipa-managed-entries
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Enables or disables the &DSF; Managed Entries Plug-in which manages user private groups.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									ipa-server-certinstall
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Replaces the current SSL certificates used with the &IPA; server with new certificates. (The certificates must be generated externally, such as using the <command>pk12util</command> tool.)
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									ipa-csreplica-manage
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Manages the replication agreements between the &DSF; instances used by the certificate authorities for a server or replica.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									ipa-nis-manage
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Enables or disables the NIS listener plug-in.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									ipa-server-install
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Installs all of the backend servers used by &IPAA; server and configures associated services and domains.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									ipa-upgradeconfig
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Upgrades the Apache instance used by the &IPA; web UI. <emphasis>Used by other scripts; not invoked by administrators directly.</emphasis>
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									ipa-replica-conncheck
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Checks the connection between &IPAA; server and a replica. This is typically run internally when a replica is installed (with <command>ipa-replica-install</command>), but can be run manually to troubleshoot connection issues.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									ipa-dns-install
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Installs and configures a DNS server for &IPAA; server which was initially configured without DNS.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									ipa-replica-install
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Installs and configures &IPAA; replica instance, based on the submitted &IPA; server configuration which was extracted using <command>ipa-replica-prepare</command>.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									ipa-getcert
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Submits requests and manages certificates for user which are issued and tracked using the <command>Certmonger</command> utility.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									ipa-getkeytab
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Requests a new keytab for &IPAA; service, host, or user.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									ipa-replica-manage
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Edits the replication agreements between &IPA; servers and replicas and synchronization agreements between the &IPA; server and &AD; domain controller.
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</table>
			</section>

		<section id="ipa-compat-manage" condition="reviewing"><title>ipa-compat-manage</title>
			<para>
				Description
			</para>
			<section id="ipa-compat-manage-location"><title>Location</title>
				<informaltable>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Description
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Location
								</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Tool directory
								</entry>
								<entry>
									&SBIN;
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Package
								</entry>
								<entry>
									ipa-server
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</informaltable>
			</section>

			<section id="ipa-compat-manage-syntax"><title>Syntax</title>
				<cmdsynopsis>
					<command>PKCS12Export</command>
					<arg choice="plain">
						-d <replaceable>/path/to/cert-directory</replaceable>
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						-debug
					</arg>
				</cmdsynopsis>
			</section>
					
			<section id="ipa-compat-manage-options"><title>Options</title>
				<informaltable>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Parameter
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Description
								</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Tool directory
								</entry>
								<entry>
									&SBIN;
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Package
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Location
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</informaltable>
			</section>
		</section>
	
		<section id="ipa-compliance" condition="reviewing"><title>ipa-compliance</title>
			<para>
				Description
			</para>
			<section id="ipa-compliance-location"><title>Location</title>
				<informaltable>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Description
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Location
								</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Tool directory
								</entry>
								<entry>
									&SBIN;
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Package
								</entry>
								<entry>
									ipa-server
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</informaltable>
			</section>

			<section id="ipa-compliance-syntax"><title>Syntax</title>
				<cmdsynopsis>
					<command>PKCS12Export</command>
					<arg choice="plain">
						-d <replaceable>/path/to/cert-directory</replaceable>
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						-debug
					</arg>
				</cmdsynopsis>
			</section>
					
			<section id="ipa-compliance-options"><title>Options</title>
				<informaltable>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Parameter
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Description
								</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Tool directory
								</entry>
								<entry>
									&SBIN;
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Package
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Location
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</informaltable>
			</section>
		</section>
	
		<section id="ipa-dns-install" condition="reviewing"><title>ipa-dns-install</title>
			<para>
				Description
			</para>
			<section id="ipa-dns-install-location"><title>Location</title>
				<informaltable>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Description
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Location
								</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Tool directory
								</entry>
								<entry>
									&SBIN;
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Package
								</entry>
								<entry>
									ipa-server
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</informaltable>
			</section>

			<section id="ipa-dns-install-syntax"><title>Syntax</title>
				<cmdsynopsis>
					<command>PKCS12Export</command>
					<arg choice="plain">
						-d <replaceable>/path/to/cert-directory</replaceable>
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						-debug
					</arg>
				</cmdsynopsis>
			</section>
					
			<section id="ipa-dns-install-options"><title>Options</title>
				<informaltable>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Parameter
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Description
								</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Tool directory
								</entry>
								<entry>
									&SBIN;
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Package
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Location
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</informaltable>
			</section>
		</section>
	
		<section id="ipa-host-net-manage" condition="reviewing"><title>ipa-host-net-manage</title>
			<para>
				Description
			</para>
			<section id="ipa-host-net-manage-location"><title>Location</title>
				<informaltable>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Description
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Location
								</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Tool directory
								</entry>
								<entry>
									&SBIN;
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Package
								</entry>
								<entry>
									ipa-server
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</informaltable>
			</section>

			<section id="ipa-host-net-manage-syntax"><title>Syntax</title>
				<cmdsynopsis>
					<command>PKCS12Export</command>
					<arg choice="plain">
						-d <replaceable>/path/to/cert-directory</replaceable>
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						-debug
					</arg>
				</cmdsynopsis>
			</section>
					
			<section id="ipa-host-net-manage-options"><title>Options</title>
				<informaltable>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Parameter
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Description
								</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Tool directory
								</entry>
								<entry>
									&SBIN;
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Package
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Location
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</informaltable>
			</section>
		</section>


	
		<section id="ipa-ldap-updater" condition="reviewing"><title>ipa-ldap-updater</title>
			<para>
				Description
			</para>
			<section id="ipa-ldap-updater-location"><title>Location</title>
				<informaltable>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Description
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Location
								</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Tool directory
								</entry>
								<entry>
									&SBIN;
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Package
								</entry>
								<entry>
									ipa-server
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</informaltable>
			</section>

			<section id="ipa-ldap-updater-syntax"><title>Syntax</title>
				<cmdsynopsis>
					<command>PKCS12Export</command>
					<arg choice="plain">
						-d <replaceable>/path/to/cert-directory</replaceable>
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						-debug
					</arg>
				</cmdsynopsis>
			</section>
					
			<section id="ipa-ldap-updater-options"><title>Options</title>
				<informaltable>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Parameter
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Description
								</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Tool directory
								</entry>
								<entry>
									&SBIN;
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Package
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Location
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</informaltable>
			</section>
		</section>
	
		<section id="ipa-nis-manage" condition="reviewing"><title>ipa-nis-manage</title>
			<para>
				Description
			</para>
			<section id="ipa-nis-manage-location"><title>Location</title>
				<informaltable>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Description
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Location
								</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Tool directory
								</entry>
								<entry>
									&SBIN;
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Package
								</entry>
								<entry>
									ipa-server
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</informaltable>
			</section>

			<section id="ipa-nis-manage-syntax"><title>Syntax</title>
				<cmdsynopsis>
					<command>PKCS12Export</command>
					<arg choice="plain">
						-d <replaceable>/path/to/cert-directory</replaceable>
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						-debug
					</arg>
				</cmdsynopsis>
			</section>
					
			<section id="ipa-nis-manage-options"><title>Options</title>
				<informaltable>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Parameter
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Description
								</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Tool directory
								</entry>
								<entry>
									&SBIN;
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Package
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Location
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</informaltable>
			</section>
		</section>
	
		<section id="ipa-replica-install"><title>ipa-replica-install</title>
			<para>
				Uses a configuration file based on an existing &IPA; server to create a replica, or copy, of that server. Once the replica is created, 
				it functions as an equal participant and mirror of the original &IPA; server within the &IPA; domain. Any changes made on the server or 
				any other replica are automatically propagated over to the other replicas and server.
			</para>
			<para>
				A replica is created using a file that contains all of the configuration for the &IPA; server. This initial file is created by running the 
				<command>ipa-replica-prepare</command> on the &IPA; server. Then the file is copied over to the replica machine, and the 
				<command>ipa-replica-install</command> script is run.
			</para>
			<para>
				As with the server and client install scripts, any replica arguments which require a parameter value (such as the Directory Manager password) will be prompted for 
				during installation, unless the argument is passed with the command. Parameters with Boolean values (like configuring DNS) will assume that the default 
				value should be used unless the argument is passed with the command.
			</para>
			<section id="ipa-replica-install-location"><title>Location</title>
				<informaltable>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Description
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Location
								</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Tool directory
								</entry>
								<entry>
									&SBIN;
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Package
								</entry>
								<entry>
									ipa-server
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</informaltable>
			</section>

			<section id="ipa-replica-install-syntax"><title>Syntax</title>
				<cmdsynopsis>
					<command>ipa-replica-install</command>
					<arg choice="opt">
						<replaceable>options</replaceable>
					</arg>
					<arg choice="plain">
						<replaceable>/path/to/replica_file</replaceable>
					</arg>
				</cmdsynopsis>
			</section>
					
			<section id="ipa-replica-install-options"><title>Options</title>
				<informaltable>
					<tgroup cols="3">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Short Parameter
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Long Parameter
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Description
								</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>
									<emphasis>file</emphasis>
								</entry>
								<entry>
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Gives the full path and filename of the replica initialization file that was created from the &IPA; server configuration.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
								</entry>
								<entry>
									--setup-ca 
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Sets up a &FCRTS; certificate authority. Otherwise, no CA is configured for the replica.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
								</entry>
								<entry>
									--ip-address=<emphasis>IPaddress</emphasis>

								</entry>
								<entry>
									Adds the host machine using its IP address, rather than the hostname.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
										    -N
								</entry>
								<entry>
									--no-ntp
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Does not configure NTP on the replica system.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
								</entry>
								<entry>
									--no-sshd
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Does not configure the OpenSSH server or client.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
								</entry>
								<entry>
									--ssh-trust-dns
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Configures the OpenSSH client for the &IPA; client to trust any domain DNS SSHFP records.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
								</entry>
								<entry>
									--no-ui-redirect
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Configures the Apache server to not automatically redirect to the &IPA; web UI, so that the web UI has to be accessed through its <filename>/ipa/ui</filename> path.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
 	    -d
								</entry>
								<entry>
									--debug
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Prints additional debug information.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
 	    -p
								</entry>
								<entry>
									--password
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Gives the Directory Manager password for the &IPA; domain.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
 	    -w
								</entry>
								<entry>
									--admin-password
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Gives the Kerberos password for the &IPA; <command>admin</command> user. This is used to check Kerberos and domain connectivity on the replica.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
								</entry>
								<entry>
 	    --setup-dns
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Sets up DNS services on the replica machine to connect to the &IPA; DNS domain. If this is not used, then the default value is false, which does not enable DNS.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
								</entry>
								<entry>
 	    --forwarder
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Gives a comma-separated list of IP addresses for DNS forwarders. 
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
								</entry>
								<entry>
 	    --no-forwarders
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Disables DNS forwarder configuration and uses only domain root servers. If this is not used, then the default value is false, which prompts for DNS forwarder information.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
								</entry>
								<entry>
 	    --reverse-zone
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Gives a DNS reverse zone to use with the replica DNS services.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
								</entry>
								<entry>
 	    --no-reverse
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Disables reverse DNS creation through the server installation process. (If a reverse DNS zone is already configured, then that existing reverse DNS zone is used.) If this option is not used, then the default value is true, which assumes that reverse DNS should be configured by the installation script.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
								</entry>
								<entry>
 	    --no-host-dns
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Disables host DNS lookups during the replica installation process. If this is not used, then the default value is true, which performs the host DNS lookups.
								</entry>
							</row>

							<row>
								<entry>
								</entry>
								<entry>
									--no-dns-sshfp 
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Configures the client to not configure DNS SSHFP records.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
								</entry>
								<entry>
 	    --skip-conncheck
								</entry>
								<entry>
									<para>
										Disables checks for the replica's connection to the &IPA; domain. If this is not used, then the default value is true, which checks that the replica can connect to the Kerberos realm. 
									</para>
									<para>
										This can be useful if the replica is unable to reach the &DS; or the CA used by the original &IPA; server, such as the server is offline or the server's firewall is blocking access on the required ports (<xref linkend="prereq-ports" />).
									</para>
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									-U
								</entry>
								<entry>
									--unattended
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Disables user prompts so that the replica installation script runs without user interaction.
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</informaltable>
			</section>
		</section>

		<section id="ipa-replica-manage" condition="reviewing"><title>ipa-replica-manage</title>
			<para>
				Description
			</para>
			<section id="ipa-replica-manage-location"><title>Location</title>
				<informaltable>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Description
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Location
								</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Tool directory
								</entry>
								<entry>
									&SBIN;
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Package
								</entry>
								<entry>
									ipa-server
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</informaltable>
			</section>

			<section id="ipa-replica-manage-syntax"><title>Syntax</title>
				<cmdsynopsis>
					<command>PKCS12Export</command>
					<arg choice="plain">
						-d <replaceable>/path/to/cert-directory</replaceable>
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						-debug
					</arg>
				</cmdsynopsis>
			</section>
					
			<section id="ipa-replica-manage-options"><title>Options</title>
				<informaltable>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Parameter
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Description
								</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Tool directory
								</entry>
								<entry>
									&SBIN;
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Package
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Location
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</informaltable>
			</section>
		</section>
	
		<section id="ipa-replica-prepare"><title>ipa-replica-prepare</title>
			<para>
				Creates a file that can be used to create a copy, or <emphasis>replica</emphasis>, of the &IPA; server. 
			</para>
			<para>
				Each replica initialization file is unique to the replica machine because the configuration is based, in part, 
				on the IP address and hostname of the replica machine. This host-specific configuration is especially critical for 
				setting up services like Kerberos which use SSL because SSL certificates are created based on the hostname. 
			</para>
			<para>
				When the replica file is created, the prep script 
				requires the hostname and, optionally, accepts the IP address. 
			</para>
			<para>
				Once the configuration file is created on the server using the <command>ipa-replica-prepare</command> command, 
				then the replica file is copied over to the replica machine and the replica is configured using the 
				<command>ipa-replica-install</command> command.
			</para>
			<note><title>NOTE</title>
				<para>
					If DNS is managed by &IPA;, then use either the <option>--ip-address</option> option or configure DNS forwarders and allow reverse DNS lookups. 
				</para>
			</note>
			<section id="ipa-replica-prepare-location"><title>Location</title>
				<informaltable>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Description
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Location
								</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Tool directory
								</entry>
								<entry>
									&SBIN;
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Package
								</entry>
								<entry>
									ipa-server
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</informaltable>
			</section>

			<section id="ipa-replica-prepare-syntax"><title>Syntax</title>
				<cmdsynopsis>
					<command>ipa-replica-prepare</command>
					<arg choice="opt">
						--dirsrv_pkcs12=<replaceable>file</replaceable>
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						--http_pkcs12=<replaceable>file</replaceable>
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						--dirsrv_pin=<replaceable>pin</replaceable>
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						--http_pin=<replaceable>pin</replaceable>
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						--ip-address=<replaceable>ipAddress</replaceable>
					</arg>
					<arg choice="plain">
						<replaceable>hostname</replaceable>
					</arg>
				</cmdsynopsis>
			</section>
					
			<section id="ipa-replica-prepare-options"><title>Options</title>
				<informaltable>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Parameter
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Description
								</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>
									       --dirsrv_pkcs12
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Gives the full path and filename of a PKCS #12 file (.p12) which contains the &DS;'s SSL certificate.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
       --dirsrv_pin
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Gives the password to access the &DS; certificate file.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
       --http_pkcs12
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Gives the full path and filename of a PKCS #12 file (.p12) which contains the Apache server's SSL certificate.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
       --http_pin
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Gives the password to access the Apache certificate file.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
       --ip-address
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Gives the IP address of the replica server. Using this option automatically adds A and PTR records for the replica host to the &IPA; DNS configuration.
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</informaltable>
			</section>
		</section>
	
		<section id="ipa-server-certinstall" condition="reviewing"><title>ipa-server-certinstall</title>
			<para>
				Description
			</para>
			<section id="ipa-server-certinstall-location"><title>Location</title>
				<informaltable>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Description
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Location
								</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Tool directory
								</entry>
								<entry>
									&SBIN;
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Package
								</entry>
								<entry>
									ipa-server
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</informaltable>
			</section>

			<section id="ipa-server-certinstall-syntax"><title>Syntax</title>
				<cmdsynopsis>
					<command>PKCS12Export</command>
					<arg choice="plain">
						-d <replaceable>/path/to/cert-directory</replaceable>
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						-debug
					</arg>
				</cmdsynopsis>
			</section>
					
			<section id="ipa-server-certinstall-options"><title>Options</title>
				<informaltable>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Parameter
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Description
								</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Tool directory
								</entry>
								<entry>
									&SBIN;
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Package
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Location
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</informaltable>
			</section>
		</section>
	
		<section id="ipa-server-install"><title>ipa-server-install</title>
			<para>
				Configures all of the services used by the &IPA; server for the &IPA; domain:
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						&FCRTS;, for issuing server certificates
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						&DSF;, for storing all of the &IPA; information
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						The Kerberos KDC, with the LDAP backend
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Apache, for the web-based services
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						NTP
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						The <command>ipa_kpasswd</command> service
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Optionally, DNS
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<para>
				This script can be run interactively, which prompts for many of the server values, or information can be passed directly to the script so that the server can be configured without human intervention. 
			</para>
			<para>
				The &IPA; server configuration is very flexible. The setup script allows some customization to services like DNS, NTP, certificate issuance, and access control in &IPA; so that the server can be suited to the network environment.
			</para>

			<section id="ipa-server-install-location"><title>Location</title>
				<informaltable>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Description
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Location
								</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Tool directory
								</entry>
								<entry>
									&SBIN;
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Package
								</entry>
								<entry>
									ipa-server
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</informaltable>
			</section>

			<section id="ipa-server-install-syntax"><title>Syntax</title>
				<cmdsynopsis>
					<command>ipa-server-install</command>
					<arg choice="plain">
						-a <replaceable>ipa_admin_password</replaceable>
					</arg>
					<arg choice="plain">
						--hostname=<replaceable>hostname</replaceable>
					</arg>
					<arg choice="plain">
						-p <replaceable>directory_manager_password</replaceable>
					</arg>
					<arg choice="plain">
						-n <replaceable>domain_name</replaceable>
					</arg>
					<arg choice="plain">
						-r <replaceable>realm_name</replaceable>
					</arg>
					<group choice="opt">
						<arg choice="opt">
							--external-ca
						</arg>
						<arg choice="opt">
							--external_ca_file=<replaceable>CA_cert_chain_file</replaceable>
						</arg>
						<arg choice="opt">
							--external_cert_file=<replaceable>certificate_file</replaceable>
						</arg>
					</group>
						<arg choice="opt">
							--selfsign
						</arg>
						<arg choice="opt">
							--subject=<replaceable>subject_DN</replaceable>
						</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						--setup-dns
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						--forwarder=<replaceable>forwarder</replaceable>
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						--no-forwarders
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						--no-reverse
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						--zone-refresh=<replaceable>seconds</replaceable>
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						--zone-notif
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						--zonemgr=<replaceable>email_address</replaceable>
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						--ip-address=<replaceable>ip_address</replaceable>
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						-P <replaceable>kerberos_master_password</replaceable>
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						--no-ntp
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						--idmax=<replaceable>number</replaceable>
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						--idstart=<replaceable>number</replaceable>
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						--no_hbac_allow
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						--no-host-dns
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						-U
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						--uninstall
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						--debug
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						--help
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						--version
					</arg>
				</cmdsynopsis>
			</section>
					
			<section id="ipa-server-install-options"><title>Options</title>
				<informaltable>
				<tgroup cols="3">
					<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" />
					<colspec colnum="2" colname="col3" />
					<colspec colnum="3" colname="col2" />
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry>
								Argument
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Alternate Argument
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Description
								</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">
								<emphasis role="bold">Required Options</emphasis><footnote><para>The installation script will prompt for these options if they are not passed with the script.</para></footnote>
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								-a <emphasis>ipa_admin_password</emphasis>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								--admin-password=<emphasis>ipa_admin_password</emphasis>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								The password for the &IPA; administrator. This is used for the admin user to authenticate to the Kerberos realm.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								--hostname=<emphasis>hostname</emphasis>
							</entry>
							<entry>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								The fully-qualified domain name of the &IPA; server machine.
							<important><title>IMPORTANT</title>
								<para>
									This must be a valid DNS name, which means only numbers, alphabetic characters, and hyphens (-) are allowed. Other characters, like underscores, in the hostname will cause DNS failures.
								</para>
								<para>
									Additionally, the hostname must all be lower-case. No capital letters are allowed.
								</para>
							</important>
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								-n <emphasis>domain_name</emphasis>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								--domain=<emphasis>domain_name</emphasis>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								The name of the LDAP server domain to use for the &IPA; domain. This is usually based on the &IPA; server's hostname.
							</entry>
						</row>
						
						<row>
							<entry>
								-p <emphasis>directory_manager_password</emphasis>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								--ds-password=<emphasis>directory_manager_password</emphasis>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								The password for the superuser, <command>cn=Directory Manager</command>, for the LDAP service.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								-r <emphasis>realm_name</emphasis>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								--realm=<emphasis>realm_name</emphasis>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								The name of the Kerberos realm to create for the &IPA; domain.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">
								<emphasis role="bold">Certificate Authority Options</emphasis>
							</entry>
						</row>
						<!--row>
							<entry>
								- -dirsrv_pin=<emphasis>pin</emphasis>
							</entry>
							<entry>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Gives the password to access the PKCS#12 file containing the &DS; certificate. If the <option>- -external-ca</option> option is used, then this option is required.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								- -dirsrv_pkcs12=<emphasis>/path/to/file</emphasis>
							</entry>
							<entry>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Gives the location of the PKCS#12 file containing the &DS; certificate. The &DS; must run over SSL, which means it requires a certificate. If the <option>- -external-ca</option> option is used, then the &DS; certificate must be generated by that external CA and supplied to the installation script.
							</entry>
						</row-->
						<row>
							<entry>
								--external-ca
							</entry>
							<entry>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Instructs the installation script to generate a certificate request that can be submitted to an external or third-party CA.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								--external_ca_file=<emphasis>CA_cert_chain_file</emphasis>
							</entry>
							<entry>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Points to the PKCS#10 file which contains the CA certificate chain of the external CA. This is required to validate the certificate issued by the CA for the &IPA; server. If an external CA is used, this is required in a second invocation of <command>ipa-server-install</command> to complete the setup process.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								--external_cert_file=<emphasis>certificate_file</emphasis>
							</entry>
							<entry>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Points to the PKCS#10 file which contains the certificate that was generated by an external CA. If an external CA is used, this is required in a second invocation of <command>ipa-server-install</command> to complete the setup process.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<!--row>
							<entry>
								- -http_pin=<emphasis>pin</emphasis>
							</entry>
							<entry>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Gives the password to access the PKCS#12 file containing the Apache certificate. If the <option>- -external-ca</option> option is used, then this option is required.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								- -http_pkcs12=<emphasis>/path/to/file</emphasis>
							</entry>
							<entry>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Gives the location of the PKCS#12 file containing the Apache server certificate. The Apache instance must run over SSL, which means it requires a certificate. If the <option>- -external-ca</option> option is used, then the Apache server certificate must be generated by that external CA and supplied to the installation script.
							</entry>
						</row-->
						<!--row>
							<entry>
								- -selfsign
							</entry>
							<entry>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Uses a self-signed certificate instead of a certificate issued by the internal &FCRTS; or by an external CA. If this option is selected, then no &FCRTS; instance is configured as part of the setup process, and the &IPA; server itself functionally serves as a CA for clients in the domain. This is not recommended for production environments, but can be used in test or development environments.
							</entry>
						</row-->
						<row>
							<entry>
								--subject=<emphasis>subject_DN</emphasis>
							</entry>
							<entry>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Sets the base element for the subject DN of the issued certificates. This defaults to <command>O=</command><emphasis>realm</emphasis>.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">
								<emphasis role="bold">DNS Options</emphasis>
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								--forwarder=<emphasis>forwarder</emphasis>
							</entry>
							<entry>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Gives a comma-separated list of DNS forwarders to use with the DNS service.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								--no-forwarders
							</entry>
							<entry>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Uses root servers with the DNS service instead of forwarders.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								--no-reverse
							</entry>
							<entry>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Disables reverse DNS creation through the server installation process. (If a reverse DNS zone is already configured, then that existing reverse DNS zone is used.) If this option is not used, then the default value is true, which assumes that reverse DNS should be configured by the installation script.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								--setup-dns
							</entry>
							<entry>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Tells the installation script to set up a DNS service within the &IPA; domain. Using an integrated DNS service is optional, so if this option is not passed with the installation script, then no DNS is configured.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								--zone-refresh=<emphasis>seconds</emphasis>
							</entry>
							<entry>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Sets whether the &IPA; server should periodically check to see when new DNS zones are added and update its DNS server accordingly. The polling interval is set in seconds.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								--zone-notif
							</entry>
							<entry>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Opens a persistent search with its &DS; and captures any new zone changes immediately.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								--zonemgr=<emphasis>email_address</emphasis>
							</entry>
							<entry>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Gives the email address to use for the DNS zone manager. If none is given, this defaults to root.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">
								<emphasis role="bold">Kerberos Options</emphasis>
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								--ip-address=<emphasis>ip_address</emphasis>
							</entry>
							<entry>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Gives the IP address of the Kerberos master KDC. This can be used if there are multiple &IPA; servers in the same realm.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								-P <emphasis>kerberos_master_password</emphasis>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								--master-password=<emphasis>kerberos_master_password</emphasis>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								The password for the KDC account. This is randomly generated if no value is given.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">
								<emphasis role="bold">NTP Options</emphasis>
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								-N, --no-ntp
							</entry>
							<entry>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Does <emphasis>not</emphasis> configure the NTP service for the &IPA; server. This is normally done by default.
								<note><title>NOTE</title>
									<para>
										If the &IPA; server is running as a virtual guest, it should not run an NTP service. 
									</para>
								</note>
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">
								<emphasis role="bold">&IPA; Server Configuration Options</emphasis>
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								--idmax=<emphasis>number</emphasis>
							</entry>
							<entry>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Sets the upper bound for IDs which can be assigned by the &IPA; server. The default value is the ID start value plus 199999.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								--idstart=<emphasis>number</emphasis>
							</entry>
							<entry>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Sets the lower bound (starting value) for IDs which can be assigned by the &IPA; server. The default value is randomly selected.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								--no_hbac_allow
							</entry>
							<entry>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Disables the <command>allow_all</command> rule for host-based access control in the &IPA; domain.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">
								<emphasis role="bold">Other Setup Options</emphasis>
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								--no-host-dns
							</entry>
							<entry>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Does <emphasis>not</emphasis> use DNS to look up the hostname of the &IPA; server machine during the installation process.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								-U
							</entry>
							<entry>
								--unattended
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Runs the <command>ipa-server-install</command> command without any interactive prompts.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								--uninstall
							</entry>
							<entry>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Uninstalls an existing &IPA; server.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">
								<emphasis role="bold">General Tool Options</emphasis>
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								-d
							</entry>
							<entry>
								--debug
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Runs the <command>ipa-server-install</command> command in debug mode and outputs debugging information.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								-h
							</entry>
							<entry>
								--help
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Prints the help information for the <command>ipa-server-install</command> command.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								--version
							</entry>
							<entry>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Prints the version number of the <command>ipa-server-install</command> command.

								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</informaltable>
			</section>
		</section>
	
		<section id="ipa-ugradeconfig" condition="reviewing"><title>ipa-upgradeconfig</title>
			<para>
				Description
			</para>
			<section id="ipa-upgradeconfig-location"><title>Location</title>
				<informaltable>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Description
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Location
								</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Tool directory
								</entry>
								<entry>
									&SBIN;
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Package
								</entry>
								<entry>
									ipa-server
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</informaltable>
			</section>

			<section id="ipa-upgradeconfig-syntax"><title>Syntax</title>
				<cmdsynopsis>
					<command>PKCS12Export</command>
					<arg choice="plain">
						-d <replaceable>/path/to/cert-directory</replaceable>
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						-debug
					</arg>
				</cmdsynopsis>
			</section>
					
			<section id="ipa-upgradeconfig-options"><title>Options</title>
				<informaltable>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Parameter
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Description
								</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Tool directory
								</entry>
								<entry>
									&SBIN;
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Package
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Location
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</informaltable>
			</section>
		</section>
	
		<section id="ipactl" condition="reviewing"><title>ipactl</title>
			<para>
				Description
			</para>
			<section id="ipactl-location"><title>Location</title>
				<informaltable>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Description
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Location
								</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Tool directory
								</entry>
								<entry>
									&SBIN;
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Package
								</entry>
								<entry>
									ipa-server
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</informaltable>
			</section>

			<section id="ipactl-syntax"><title>Syntax</title>
				<cmdsynopsis>
					<command>PKCS12Export</command>
					<arg choice="plain">
						-d <replaceable>/path/to/cert-directory</replaceable>
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						-debug
					</arg>
				</cmdsynopsis>
			</section>
					
			<section id="ipactl-options"><title>Options</title>
				<informaltable>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Parameter
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Description
								</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Tool directory
								</entry>
								<entry>
									&SBIN;
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Package
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Location
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</informaltable>
			</section>
		</section>
	</section>


	<section id="client-tools"><title>Client Scripts</title>
		<para>
			These tools are used to manage client machines.
		</para>

		<section id="ipa-client-install"><title>ipa-client-install</title>
			<para>
				Configures a client machine. This script uses the local SSSD service to connect to the &IPA; server during the setup process. It is also possible to 
				connect to the server through PAM/NSS using LDAP.
			</para>
			<para>
				This script is also used to uninstall clients, which removes them from the &IPA; domain and removes all &IPA;-related configuration.
			</para>
			<para>
				This script is only available for &OS; platforms.
			</para>
			<section id="ipa-client-install-location"><title>Location</title>
				<informaltable>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Description
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Location
								</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Tool directory
								</entry>
								<entry>
									/usr/sbin/
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Package
								</entry>
								<entry>
									ipa-client
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</informaltable>
			</section>

			<section id="ipa-client-install-syntax"><title>Syntax</title>
				<cmdsynopsis>
					<command>ipa-client-install</command>
					<arg choice="opt">
						-d | --debug
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						--domain=<replaceable>domainName</replaceable>
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						--enable-dns-updates
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						-f, --force
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						--hostname=<replaceable>clientHostname</replaceable>
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						--mkhomedir
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						-N, --no-ntp
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						--no-krb5-offline-passwords
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						-ntp-server=<replaceable>NTP_server</replaceable>
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						--ssh-trust-dns
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						--no-sshd
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						--no-dns-sshfp 
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						--on-master
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						-p | --principal
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						--permit
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						--realm=<replaceable>realmName</replaceable>
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						-S | --no-sssd
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						--preserve-sssd
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						--server=<replaceable>IPA_server_fqdn</replaceable>
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						-U | --unattended
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						--uninstall
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						-w <replaceable>password</replaceable> | --password=<replaceable>password</replaceable> | -W
					</arg>
				</cmdsynopsis>
			</section>
					
			<section id="ipa-client-install-options"><title>Options</title>
				<informaltable>
					<tgroup cols="3">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Long Parameter
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Short Parameter
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Description
								</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>
									--domain=<replaceable>domainName</replaceable>
								</entry>
								<entry>
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Gives the domain name for the &IPA; domain.
      </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
								<entry>
	      --enable-dns-updates
      </entry>
      <entry>
								</entry>
								<entry>
              Tells SSSD to update DNS with the IP
              address of this client.
	      
									
								</entry>
								
							</row>
							<row>
	     <entry>
		    --force
	      </entry>
								<entry>
	      -f
	     </entry>
								<entry>
									Forces the script to apply the settings even if errors occur.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
								<entry>

	      --hostname=<replaceable>clientHostname</replaceable>
      </entry>
      <entry>
								</entry>
								<entry>
              Sets the fully-qualified domain name of the client server. If this is not given, the script uses the nodename given in uname.
							<important><title>IMPORTANT</title>
								<para>
									This must be a valid DNS name, which means only numbers, alphabetic characters, and hyphens (-) are allowed. Other characters, like underscores, in the hostname will cause DNS failures.
								</para>
								<para>
									Additionally, the hostname must all be lower-case. No capital letters are allowed.
								</para>
							</important>
	      </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
								<entry>

	      --mkhomedir
      </entry>
      <entry>
								</entry>
								<entry>
              Configures PAM to create a user's home directory if it does not exist.
	      </entry>
      </row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									--no-dns-sshfp 
								</entry>
								<entry>
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Configures the client to not configure DNS SSHFP records.
								</entry>
							</row>
      <row>
								<entry>
	      --no-ntp
	      </entry>
								<entry>

	      -N
	      </entry>
								<entry>
									Does not configure or enable NTP.
									</entry>
								</row>
      <row>
								<entry>

	      </entry>
								<entry>
		--no-krb5-offline-passwords
	      </entry>
								<entry>
									Prevents the SSSD services from storing Kerberos passwords in the SSSD cache. The cache is useful because a user may log into a system when a machine is offline and then attempt to access domain services after the machine is brought online. Using the cache stores the password, which can be referenced when the domain is accessed.
									</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									--no-sshd
								</entry>
								<entry>
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Does not configure the OpenSSH server or client.
								</entry>
							</row>
								<row>
								<entry>

	      --ntp-server=<replaceable>NTP_server</replaceable>
      </entry>
      <entry>
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Configures the local <systemitem>ntpd</systemitem> service to use the &IPA; NTP server.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
								<entry>

	      --on-master
      </entry>
      <entry>
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Indicates the client is being configured on &IPAA; server. This is not for a normal invocation of the setup script; this option is used by <command>ipa-server-install</command> when a server is configured.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
								<entry>
	     --principal
       </entry>
								<entry>

	     -p
	     </entry>
								<entry>
									Passes an authorized Kerberos principal to use to join the &IPA; realm. This is used during an automated deployment, such as a kickstart process.
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
								<entry>

	      --permit
	      </entry>
<entry>
								</entry>	      <entry>
              Configures SSSD to permit all access. If this is not set, then access to the client is controlled by the host-based access controls on the &IPA; server.
	      </entry>
      </row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									--preserve-sssd
								</entry>
								<entry>
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Preserves the original SSSD configuration rather than updating it for &IPA;-specific changes, such as SSH key caching.
								</entry>
							</row>
      <row>
								<entry>

	      --realm=<replaceable>realmName</replaceable>
      </entry>
      <entry>
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Gives the &IPA; realm name.
									</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
								<entry>
									--no-sssd
	      </entry>
								<entry>

									-S
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Tells the client to use <systemitem>nss_ldap</systemitem> for authentication instead of SSSD.
	      </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
								<entry>
	      --server=<replaceable>IPA_server_fqdn</replaceable>
      </entry>
      <entry>
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Gives the name of the &IPA; server to connect to. This must be a fully-qualified domain name.
							<important><title>IMPORTANT</title>
								<para>
									This must be a valid DNS name, which means only numbers, alphabetic characters, and hyphens (-) are allowed. Other characters, like underscores, in the hostname will cause DNS failures.
								</para>
							</important>
									</entry>
      </row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									--ssh-trust-dns
								</entry>
								<entry>
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Configures the OpenSSH client for the &IPA; client to trust any domain DNS SSHFP records.
								</entry>
							</row>
      
      
      
      <row>
								<entry>
									--unattended
									</entry>
								<entry>

	      -U
	      </entry>
								<entry>
									Performs an unattended installation, with no user prompts.
									</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
								<entry>

	      --uninstall
      </entry>
      <entry>
								</entry>
								<entry>
              Removes the &IPA; client software and configuration to restore the machine to a pre-&IPA; state.
	      </entry>
      </row>
      
      
      
      <row>
								<entry>
	     --password=<emphasis>password</emphasis>
	      </entry>
								<entry>

									-w <emphasis>password</emphasis>
	      </entry>
								<entry>
              Gives the Kerberos password to use to access the &IPA; realm and join the machine. If only the password parameter is used, the script assumes this is a bulk enrollment and uses the machine name as the Kerberos principal. If the principal is given, the script binds as an &IPA; user.
	      </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
      <entry>
								</entry>
								<entry>

	      -W
      </entry>
								<entry>
									Prompts for the password.
									</entry>
      </row>
      
      
      
      
      
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</informaltable>
			</section>
		</section>
	
		<section id="ipa-getkeytab" condition="reviewing"><title>ipa-getkeytab</title>
			<para>
				Description
			</para>
			<section id="ipa-getkeytab-location"><title>Location</title>
				<informaltable>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Description
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Location
								</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Tool directory
								</entry>
								<entry>
									&SBIN;
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Package
								</entry>
								<entry>
									ipa-server
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</informaltable>
			</section>

			<section id="ipa-getkeytab-syntax"><title>Syntax</title>
				<cmdsynopsis>
					<command>PKCS12Export</command>
					<arg choice="plain">
						-d <replaceable>/path/to/cert-directory</replaceable>
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						-debug
					</arg>
				</cmdsynopsis>
			</section>
					
			<section id="ipa-getkeytab-options"><title>Options</title>
				<informaltable>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Parameter
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Description
								</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Tool directory
								</entry>
								<entry>
									&SBIN;
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Package
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Location
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</informaltable>
			</section>
		</section>
	
		<section id="ipa-join" condition="reviewing"><title>ipa-join</title>
			<para>
				Description
			</para>
			<section id="ipa-join-location"><title>Location</title>
				<informaltable>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Description
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Location
								</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Tool directory
								</entry>
								<entry>
									&SBIN;
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Package
								</entry>
								<entry>
									ipa-server
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</informaltable>
			</section>

			<section id="ipa-join-syntax"><title>Syntax</title>
				<cmdsynopsis>
					<command>PKCS12Export</command>
					<arg choice="plain">
						-d <replaceable>/path/to/cert-directory</replaceable>
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						-debug
					</arg>
				</cmdsynopsis>
			</section>
					
			<section id="ipa-join-options"><title>Options</title>
				<informaltable>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Parameter
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Description
								</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Tool directory
								</entry>
								<entry>
									&SBIN;
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Package
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Location
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</informaltable>
			</section>
		</section>
	
		<section id="ipa-rmkeytab" condition="reviewing"><title>ipa-rmkeytab</title>
			<para>
				Description
			</para>
			<section id="ipa-rmkeytab-location"><title>Location</title>
				<informaltable>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Description
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Location
								</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Tool directory
								</entry>
								<entry>
									&SBIN;
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Package
								</entry>
								<entry>
									ipa-server
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</informaltable>
			</section>

			<section id="ipa-rmkeytab-syntax"><title>Syntax</title>
				<cmdsynopsis>
					<command>PKCS12Export</command>
					<arg choice="plain">
						-d <replaceable>/path/to/cert-directory</replaceable>
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						-debug
					</arg>
				</cmdsynopsis>
			</section>
					
			<section id="ipa-rmkeytab-options"><title>Options</title>
				<informaltable>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Parameter
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Description
								</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Tool directory
								</entry>
								<entry>
									&SBIN;
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Package
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Location
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</informaltable>
			</section>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section id="certmonger-tools" condition="reviewing"><title>Certmonger Scripts</title>
		<para>
			XXXXXXXXXXXXX
		</para>

		<section id="getcert"><title>getcert</title>
			<para>
				Description
			</para>
			<section id="getcert-location"><title>Location</title>
				<informaltable>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Description
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Location
								</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Tool directory
								</entry>
								<entry>
									&SBIN;
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Package
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Location
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</informaltable>
			</section>

			<section id="getcert-syntax"><title>Syntax</title>
				<cmdsynopsis>
					<command>PKCS12Export</command>
					<arg choice="plain">
						-d <replaceable>/path/to/cert-directory</replaceable>
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						-debug
					</arg>
				</cmdsynopsis>
			</section>
					
			<section id="getcert-options"><title>Options</title>
				<informaltable>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Parameter
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Description
								</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Tool directory
								</entry>
								<entry>
									&SBIN;
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Package
								</entry>
								<entry>
									certmonger
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</informaltable>
			</section>
		</section>

		<section id="ipa-getcert"><title>ipa-getcert</title>
			<para>
				Description
			</para>
			<section id="ipa-getcert-location"><title>Location</title>
				<informaltable>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Description
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Location
								</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Tool directory
								</entry>
								<entry>
									&BIN;
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Package
								</entry>
								<entry>
									certmonger
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</informaltable>
			</section>

			<section id="ipa-getcert-syntax"><title>Syntax</title>
				<cmdsynopsis>
					<command>PKCS12Export</command>
					<arg choice="plain">
						-d <replaceable>/path/to/cert-directory</replaceable>
					</arg>
					<arg choice="opt">
						-debug
					</arg>
				</cmdsynopsis>
			</section>
					
			<section id="ipa-getcert-options"><title>Options</title>
				<informaltable>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Parameter
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Description
								</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Tool directory
								</entry>
								<entry>
									&SBIN;
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>
									Package
								</entry>
								<entry>
									Location
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</informaltable>
			</section>
		</section>
	</section>

</appendix>

